<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An historical vindication of The naked Gospel recommended to the University of Oxford.</title>
            <author>Le Clerc, Jean, 1657-1736.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L816</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21019</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12405156</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12405156</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61363</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61363)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 281:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An historical vindication of The naked Gospel recommended to the University of Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Le Clerc, Jean, 1657-1736.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pamphlets on the question of allegiance to William and Mary and on the doctrine of the Trinity, 1689-1693.</note>
                  <note>"The substance of the 'Historical vindication of 'The naked Gospel' was incorporated by M. Le Clerc into his life of Eusebius which led to the suspicion, that he was himself the author of that 'Vindication.' "--Wallace, R. Antitrinitarian biography, 1850, v. 1, 9. 207.</note>
                  <note>Written by Jean Le Clerc in support of Arthur Bury's Naked Gospel. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bury, Arthur, 1624-1713. --  Naked Gospel.</term>
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61363:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61363:1"/>
            <p>An Hiſtorical VINDICATION OF THE Naked Goſpel, Recommended to the Vniverſity of Oxford.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61363:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61363:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Deſign of this Work is of no leſs Importance than to diſcover the <hi>Naked Truth,</hi> as far as 'tis poſſible, after the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of ſuch infinite Numbers of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes by the Barbarity of former Ages: The little Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Gleanings whereof, (that accidentally eſcap'd the Flames and Fury of thoſe Times) tho' diſpers'd up and down, yet do ſtill afford ſome Light to a perſpicacious <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirer;</hi> and indeed give ſuch a Landskip of things, as the Ruins now at <hi>Athens, Carthage</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> do of thoſe Majeſtick Cities. We may ſtill plainly ſee, how the ſimple Primitive Chaſtity of the Goſpel was defil'd with the Ceremonies, and the vain <hi>Philoſophy</hi> of the <hi>Pagans:</hi> How <hi>Platonic Enthuſiaſm</hi> was impos'd upon the World for <hi>Faith, Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> by cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd Eccleſiaſticks; <hi>Qui omnia quae putabant Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſmo conducere, Biblijs interſeruerunt,</hi> as any one may collect from <hi>Eraſmus, Scaliger, Grotius, Cappellus,</hi> and <hi>F. Simons,</hi> who had compar'd Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts. Their dogmatical Contradictions in Councils, their ſilly Quarrels, their frequent changes in Opinion, their childiſh trifling in Words, their Inconſtancy, Pride, and other Paſſions are laid open, as the Source of publick
<pb facs="tcp:61363:3"/>Troubles and common Calamities. We may juſtly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Joſeph Scaliger</hi> the cruel Suppreſſion of the old Books that were in the hands of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> for if we had them now in our Libraries, <hi>Nous verrions des belles choſes,</hi> ſays that Prodigy of Learning, who in another place complains, <hi>Nihil fuit erga bonas literas injurioſius veteribus Chriſtianis; ſi voluiſſent, habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remus tam praeclara.</hi>— But conſidering how they handed things down to us, <hi>Je ne me ferois jamais Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtien a lire les Peres, Ils ont tant de Fadaiſes.</hi> Scalig.</p>
            <p>In our own time we have ſeen the ſame Phrenzy acted over again, <hi>Academick</hi> Inquiſitors (like ſupream infallible Tribunals) burning Articles and Books, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards embracing and practiſing the very ſame; expelling and recalling, canting and recanting, after the manners of their <hi>Fore-fathers,</hi> who veer'd about with every Wind, and were very angry that the Laity would not believe things againſt their Senſe and Reaſon, as the Woman would have had her Husband againſt his own Eyes: What! Believe your Eyes before your own ſweet Wife?</p>
            <p>The moſt conſiderable Parts of the preſent Vindication are, <hi>I.</hi> The Hiſtory of <hi>Plato</hi>'s Trinity. <hi>II.</hi> The <hi>Arian</hi> Controverſie. <hi>III.</hi> Of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council. <hi>IV.</hi> Of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed. <hi>V.</hi> Of the Quarrels and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of the Churches: <hi>Which take as follows.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61363:3"/>
            <head>A Modeſt and Hiſtorical VINDICATION, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat this work may be clear and inſtructive, 'tis thought neceſſary to obſerve Method and Order of Time, which are the chief lights in Hiſtorical Controverſies; Therefore we will begin with the moſt learned Biſhop of the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> was born in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and perhaps at <hi>Caeſarea;</hi>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Ap. Socrat. lib.</hi> v. c. 8.</note> for he ſays in the beginning of his Letter to the Chriſtians of that City, <hi>That he was there baptized, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Chriſtian Faith.</hi> He was born towards the end of the third Century; though we cannot find exactly the year of his Birth. He began early to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to Learning, eſpecially to Divinity, as it ſufficiently appears in his Writings, wherein may be ſeen, that he had carefully read all ſorts of Books; and that all the Chriſtian Writings, whether Greek or Latin, were well known to him. He had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the curious Library, which the Martyr <hi>Pamphilius,</hi> his particular Friend, had collected at <hi>Caeſarea.</hi>
               <note n="(b)">Hieron. Ep. ad Chron &amp; He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liod. Antipater Boſtrenſis in concil. Nicaen. <hi>11. Act. 5.</hi>
               </note> It's affirm'd, That being become Biſhop of this City, he entreated <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> (who paſſed through it, and who had bid him ask ſome favour in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of his Church) That he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to make a ſearch into all the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61363:4"/>publick Regiſters, to extract the Names of all the Martyrs, and the time of their Death. However, he has committed Faults enough in Chronology, as <hi>Joſeph Scaliger,</hi> and a great many other learned Men have obſerved, and eſpecially in relation to Martyrs, as Mr. <hi>Dodwel</hi> has lately ſhewn in his Diſſertation, <hi>de paucitate Martyrum.</hi> But it was no eaſie matter to eſcape theſe kind of Faults in ſuch a work as his Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory, which was the firſt of that ſort that was ever undertaken; the Primitive Chriſtians taking no care of the Hiſtory of their Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> is commonly called the Son of <hi>Pamphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius;</hi> whether he was really his Son, as ſome affirm, or his Nephew, according to the opinion of others; or in fine, as moſt believe, by reaſon of the great Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between them. This <hi>Pamphilius</hi> was of <hi>Beryte</hi> in <hi>Phenicia,</hi> and Prieſt of <hi>Caeſarea;</hi> he held <hi>Origen</hi>'s Opinions, for whom he wrote an Apology, of which there remains to us, but a part of it in Latin, among the Works of <hi>Origen</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome.</hi> He made it in Priſon, where he was put in the year 307, under the Emperour <hi>Decius,</hi> and where <hi>Euſebius</hi> did not forſake him. He could write only the firſt five Books, having been hindred from finiſhing<note n="(a)">Photius. cod. CXVIII.</note> this Work, by the Death which he ſuffered for the Goſpel two years after he had been thrown into Priſon. But <hi>Euſebius</hi> finiſh'd it, in add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereto a ſixth Book, and publiſh'd it after his Death. <hi>Pamphilius</hi> had for Maſter, <hi>Pierius</hi>
               <note n="(b)">Id. Cod. CXIX.</note> Prieſt of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who likewiſe ſuffered Martyrdom, and was alſo of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi>'s Opinion, whoſe Aſſiduity and Eloquence he imitated, which got him the name of ſecond <hi>Origen.</hi> It's not amiſs here to relate the Judgment which <hi>Photius</hi> makes of his Works.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61363:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>He advances ſeveral things,</hi> ſays he, <hi>remote from thoſe which are at preſent eſtabliſh'd in the Church, perhaps ac-cording to the Cuſtom of the Anoients: Yet he ſpeaks after a pious manner of the Father and the Son, excepting that he aſſures us, They have two Eſſences,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>and two Natures,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>uſing the words Eſſence and Nature, as it appears by what precedes, and follows in this Paſſage, for that of</hi> Hypoſtaſis, <hi>and not in the ſenſe of the</hi> Arians. <hi>But he ſpeaks of the Holy Spirit in a dangerous manner, for he attributes to him, a Glory inferiour to that of the Father and the Son;</hi> yet he was Catechiſt of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> under the Patriarch <hi>Theonas,</hi> who was conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated in the year 282.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pamphilius</hi> being dead, as has been ſaid, <hi>Euſebius</hi> retired to <hi>Paulinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tyre,</hi> his Friend; where he was witneſs,<note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. c. 7.</note> as he tells us himſelf, of ſeveral Martyrdoms, the Hiſtory of which he has left us, in his Book of <hi>the Martyrs of</hi> Paleſtine. From thence he went into <hi>Egypt,</hi> where he found the Perſecution yet more violent, and where he was thrown into Priſon. But this Perſecution having ceaſed, he was ſet at Liberty, and a while after elected Biſhop of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> after the death of <hi>Agapius.</hi> It's not certainly known in what year this Election was made, but at leaſt, he was already Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, when <hi>Paulinus</hi> dedicated a ſtately Church in the City of <hi>Tyre,</hi> which he had built there, which was in the year 316, in the 10th year of <hi>Conſtantin</hi>'s Reign; for it was the cuſtom of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,<note n="(b)">
                  <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Diſſ. bypat. par.</hi> 11. c. 3. n. 12, 13.</note> as well as of the Pagans, to conſecrate their Churches in the time of the Decennales of the Emperours, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Solemnity. <hi>Euſebius</hi> recites a fine Oration, ſpoken at this Dedication,<note n="(c)">
                  <hi>Lib. x.</hi> c. 4.</note> and tho' he does not ſay, that it was he himſelf
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61363:5"/>that ſpoke it, yet the ſtyle of this Oration, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt manner after which he mentions him that made it, gives one reaſon to believe, that he has ſuppreſs'd his name only through Modeſty. One might imagine, that he was then but Prieſt, were it not manifeſt, that it was very rare in that Age for Prieſts to ſpeak in publick, where there were <hi>Biſhops</hi> preſent.</p>
            <p>It was about this time, that <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> had a bickering with one of his Prieſts named <hi>Arius,</hi> touching the Divinity of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which gave Birth to <hi>Arianiſm. Euſebius</hi> having had a great ſhare in the Diſputes of Arianiſm, we cannot recount his Life without writing the Hiſtory of it; and to know wherein conſiſted theſe Diſputes, we muſt neceſſarily aſcend higher, and enquire what Principles of Philoſophy were in uſe in that time among the Chriſtians, and how they came to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced. This is ſo neceſſary a Digreſſion, as will appear in the Sequel, that it's to be ſuppoſed, the Reader muſt approve of it.</p>
            <p>There was never any Philoſopher that made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo famous as <hi>Plato,</hi> and no Books read with more pleaſure than his, whether from the Subjects, and lofty Thoughts found therein, on by reaſon of the Elegancy and Nobleneſs of their Style, which never any Philoſopher could equalize. He was born under the Reign of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> Sirnam'd <hi>Long-hand,</hi> 426 years before Chriſt, and died aged fourſcore years, in the time when <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be fear'd of all <hi>Greece. Alexander</hi> his Son hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made himſelf maſter of <hi>Aſia,</hi> which his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors divided among them; one may reaſonably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Sciences of the <hi>Greeks</hi> there, eſtabliſh'd themſelves with their Empire, and their Cuſtoms.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61363:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ptolomy</hi> the Son of <hi>Lagus,</hi> one of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, undertook to collect into his Library of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> all the Books he could find, and drew thither ſeveral learned men of <hi>Greece.</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Vid. Hody de <hi>70.</hi> Int. c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> He was learned himſelf, and omitted nothing, for the inſpiring into his Sons the love of Learning.</p>
            <p>His Son <hi>Philadelphus</hi> march'd, in this reſpect, in his Fathers ſteps, as all thoſe who have any knowledge in the Hiſtory of this Prince, do well know. The <hi>Syrian</hi> Monarchs ſeem likewiſe to have cultivated the Sciences, ſeeing that <hi>Suidas</hi> relates, that <hi>Euphorion</hi> of <hi>Chalcis</hi> in <hi>Eubea,</hi> Poet and Philoſopher, was Library-keeper of <hi>Antiochus</hi> the great, two hundred years before our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's time. <hi>Plato</hi> was too famous then, and his Works in too great eſteem, not to have had Place in theſe Libraries. One may alſo believe, that <hi>Aſia,</hi> which was then full of Greek Philoſophers, wanted not <hi>Platoniſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the Opinions of <hi>Plato,</hi> there are not any more remarkable, than thoſe which he had touching the Divinity, the Prae-exiſtence and Immortality of the Soul. He held that there is only one Supream, Spiritual, and Inviſible God, whom he calls <hi>The Being,</hi> or, the <hi>Being it ſelf,</hi> the <hi>very Being, The Father, and cauſe of all Beings,</hi> &amp;c. He placed under this ſupream God an inferiour Being, which he calls <hi>Reaſon,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>The Director of things preſent and future, the Creator of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> &amp;c. In fine, he acknowledged a third Being, which he calls the <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Soul</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi> He added, That the firſt was the Father of the ſecond, and that the ſecond had produced the third. We may conſult hereupon his <hi>Timoeus,</hi> to which we ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn his II. and VI. Letter. In the ſecond, which is directed to <hi>Denys,</hi> who complained, that <hi>Plato</hi> had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61363:6"/>not ſufficiently inſtructed him touching the <hi>firſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or firſt Being, this Philoſopher thus expreſſes himſelf. <hi>Every thing is about the King of all things, and every thing is becauſe of him; he is the cauſe of all good things: The things of the ſecond Order, are about the ſecond; the things of the third, are about the third.</hi> He calls this a Riddle; forbids <hi>Denys</hi> to ſpeak of it before the ignorant; enjoyns him to burn his Letter as ſoon as he has read it, and proteſts he will never write again of this matter. In his ſixth Letter, he enjoyns <hi>Hermias Eraſtus</hi> and <hi>Coriſca</hi> to ſwear, in tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to witneſs, <hi>the God who is the Director of things preſent and future, and the Lord, who is the Father of this Director and of this Cauſe.</hi> The Obſcurity which he affects in this occaſion, leſt he ſhould draw on him the Rage of the Superſtitious Populace, hinders us from underſtanding what he would ſay, unleſs we col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late together all the Paſſages wherein he ſpeaks of the Divinity, and conſult his Interpreters and Diſciples.</p>
            <p>Here's how one of 'em<note n="(a)">Hierocles de provid. apud Photium. Cod. CCLI.</note> explains his his Maſters meaning: <hi>Plato believed, that God the Creator ſuſtains the viſible and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible World, which was made out of nothing; That his Will ſuffices to make Beings exiſt; That by the conjunction of a corporal Nature, and another incorporal, he has made a moſt perfect World, which is double and ſingle at the ſame time, in which one may diſtinguiſh the high, the middle, and the low; That he calls high, the Heavenly Beings, and the Gods; The middle, the Aethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Intelligences and good Demons, which are the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters and Meſſengers, in what relates to the good of men; The low, the terreſtrial Intelligences, and the Souls of men, or men Immortal; That the ſuperiour Beings govern the inferiour, but that God who is the Creator and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of 'em, reigns over all; and that this paternal
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61363:6"/>Empire, is nothing elſe but his Providence, by which he gives to every ſont of Being what belongs to it.</hi> We may hereby underſtand what <hi>Plato</hi> calls the things of the ſecond and third Order. We ſhall not buſie our ſelves in ſeeking from whom <hi>Plato</hi> might have learnt this Doctrin, whether from the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> or from the Old Teſtament, as ſome of the Fathers have believ'd.</p>
            <p>Altho' <hi>Plato</hi>'s Diſciples are agreed with their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, in reſpect of theſe three Principles, yet there is to be found in their Writings divers Enquiries touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their nature, and divers ways of ſpeaking, which are not to be ſeen in thoſe of this Philoſopher, who never dared to write all he thought on this ſubject. <hi>Plotinus</hi> particularly, who liv'd in the beginning of the third Century, has treated of them, in ſeveral places of his <hi>Enneades,</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Praeſertim En. V. lib. <hi>1.</hi> a cap. <hi>3.</hi> ad <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> but eſpecially in the Book which is intitled <hi>of the three Hypoſtaſes, which are the three Principles of all things.</hi> Here's whereunto his Doctrin may be reduced.
<list>
                  <item>I. There are three Principles: <hi>The Being, the Spirit,</hi> or <hi>the Reaſon of the Being,</hi> and <hi>the Soul of the World, which is the Reaſon of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> There is alſo, according to him, <hi>a Reaſon of the Soul of the World,</hi> but it is a Reaſon <hi>obſcure;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</item>
                  <item>II. The Being has begotten the Reaſon, not by an act of his will, or by a decree, but by his nature, as fire begets heat, or as the ſun produces light. The Reaſon has alſo begotten the Soul of the World, and perhaps termed Father in this reſpect.</item>
                  <item>III. Theſe three Hypoſtaſes differ in number, altho' there be a moſt ſtrict union between them; which makes, that one may ſay at the ſame time, that they are different, and that they are the ſame thing. The firſt is more excellent than the ſecond, and the ſecond more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61363:7"/>than the third.</item>
                  <item>IV. The terms which <hi>Ploti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> uſes, are worth obſerving.
<list>
                        <item>1. He calls not only eſſence (<gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>) after <hi>Plato,</hi> the nature of the being, of the reaſon and of the ſoul of the World, but he likewiſe uſes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>matter,</hi> and ſays, that the matter of the one is more perfect than that of the other. Having pretended that <hi>Parmenides</hi> had ſaid before <hi>Plato,</hi> that there are three Principles, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes himſelf in theſe terms: <hi>Parmenides holds like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Opinion of the three Natures.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. It's obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that the word <hi>hypoſtaſis</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>) ſignifies two things with this Philoſopher; firſt, the <hi>exiſtence</hi> of a thing, conſidered abſtractedly; and in the ſecond place, the thing it ſelf which exiſts, as it's taken in the Title of this Book, of <hi>the three Hypoſtaſes,</hi> which are the Principles of all things, <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, and in the Title of the third Book of the ſame <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neade,</hi> of <hi>intelligent Beings.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. As he ſays, That the Reaſon is the Father of the Soul, he ſays likewiſe, that the Reaſon <hi>begets,</hi> and <hi>makes</hi> the Soul; for we muſt obſerve, that in this matter, <hi>Plato</hi> and his Diſciples uſe indifferently the words, <hi>to beget, to make, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce,</hi> &amp;c. and that <hi>begotten</hi> and <hi>made,</hi> is the ſame thing here, in their mouths. We need only read <hi>Plato</hi>'s <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4. <hi>Plotinus</hi> ſays, that the Father and the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon are <hi>one and the ſame thing</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, becauſe <hi>they coexist and for ſake not one another.</hi> He ſays, that the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Being, and whoſe eſſence conſiſts <hi>in exiſting,</hi> in a manner wholly particular, has begotten by his Nature the Spirit, and that he cannot be without him, no more than a luminous body can be without light.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Spirit on his part, whoſe eſſence conſiſts in having perpetually a lively conception of the Being, cannot exiſt (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) without this. They cannot be
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61363:7"/>ſeparated (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) one from the other, becauſe there is nothing between them, as there is nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Spirit and the Soul. 5. He ſays, that that which is begotten, reſembles (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) its cauſe juſt as the Light reſembles the Sun. 6. He ſays, that the Spirit is the Image (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as the Soul is the Image of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in his Eighth Book againſt <hi>Julian,</hi> cites a paſſage of <hi>Porphyry,</hi> out of his Third Book of the Philoſophical Hiſtory, whence it appears That the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> diſputed among themſelves, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there could be more than three <hi>Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in the Divinity; <hi>Plato,</hi> ſaith <hi>Porphyry, has taught, that the Divine Eſſence may extend it ſelf even to three Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; to wit, the Supream Divinity, or the good it ſelf; after it, the Creator, who is the ſecond; and the Soul of the World, which is the third,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But there are Men who pretend, that we muſt not reckon the very good, or good it ſelf, among the things which he has produced, and that being of a perfect ſimplicity, and incapable of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, he has communion with nothing: ſo that it is by the Spirit that we muſt begin to reckon the Trinity</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, <hi>Porphyry</hi>'s Maſter, whom we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready cited, ſeems<note n="(a)">Ennead. V. lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> to ſay, that there may be more than three <hi>Hypoſtaſes,</hi> in theſe remarkable words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God has begotten an excellent Being, and has brought forth all things in him. This production has cost him no pain, for pleaſing himſelf in what he beg at, and finding his productions good, he has retained them all in himſelf, tempering his brightneſs and theirs. Thoſe which have there remain'd being more excellent, there's only his only Son</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Jupiter <hi>who has appear'd without, by whom
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61363:8"/>as by the ſupream Son of the Divinity, and as in an Image, one may ſee what the Father is, and the Brethren which have remained in the Father,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Platoniſts</hi> likewiſe uſed, in ſpeaking of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which they conceiv'd to be between the different Orders of their Divinities, the Terms of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>of different Eſſence,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Co-eſſential.</hi> By the firſt, they denote the different ſorts of Beings, and by the ſecond, what is of the ſame kind. Here's a Proof taken out of <hi>Jamblichus,</hi> in his Book of the Myſteries of the Egyptians, <hi>Sect.</hi> 1. <hi>ch. xix.</hi> He ſpeaks of the manner after which the Superiour Gods are united to the Inferiour, according to the Platonic Philoſophy: <hi>The Divinities,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of the ſecond Order, turning themſelves towards the firſt intellectual Beings, and the firſt giving to the ſecond, the ſame Eſſence,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>and the ſame Power; this entertains their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion. What we call <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in the things which are of different kinds,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>as the Soul and the Body, or which are divers Species,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>as material things; or which are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe divided, this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, I ſay, happens to 'em from ſuperiour things, and deſtroys it ſelf at a certain time. But the more we elevate our ſelves to ſuperiour things, and to the Identity</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>of the firſt Beings, and in regard of the Species, and in regard of the Eſſence; when we aſcend from the parts to the whole, the more we acknowledge the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>which is eternal, and the more we ſee what is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion properly ſo called, and the Model whereon all the reſt have been form'd, and that it hath about it, and in it ſelf, the Diverſity</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>and the Multiplicity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Porphyry</hi> had ask'd, whether a kind of Being is form'd, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) mixt with our Soul and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſpiration, which made the Prophets able to foreſee the future. <hi>Jamblichus</hi>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 21.</note> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61363:8"/>
               <hi>no;</hi> and gives this reaſon for it; <hi>which is, that when one only thing is form'd of two, the whole is of one and the ſame Species, of the ſame Nature, and Co eſſential,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>and that this does not happen in the caſe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Porphyry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One may ſee hereby, the Subtilty with which the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> handled theſe Matters, and the Terms they uſed. But we ſhould take notice of two things, in endeavouring to form to our ſelves an Idea of their Sentiments. The firſt, that we muſt not always ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they had a clear and diſtinct knowledge of what they would ſay themſelves, and that they ſaw all the conſequences of their Opinions: So that it would be perhaps in vain, to endeavour to draw out of their Writings a clear Idea of their Sentiment, touching the three Principles of all things, becauſe, perhaps they themſelves conceiv'd not clearly what they ſaid; at leaſt, their Style is ſo different on this Occaſion, from that which is obſervable in the Paſſages of their Writings, wherein they ſpeak of things which they may know, that it is apparent, they contain'd not the ſubject of the three Principles, like an infinite of others, which they have known how to expreſs in an even, clear, and elegant manner. The ſecond thing we ſhould obſerve, is, That in ſo difficult a matter, we muſt content our ſelves with what they ſay po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively, without attempting to draw far-fetch'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences from their Principles, which we cannot un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand but by halfs; otherwiſe we are in danger of attributing to them, ſuch Notions as they never had. Neither muſt we endeavour to reconcile in ſo abſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſubject, the contradictions which ſeem to appear in their Doctrin, nor conclude, that they could not mean things in ſuch a manner, becauſe then they muſt contradict themſelves. It was the cuſtom of theſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61363:9"/>Philoſophers to affect certain apparent Contradictions, in uſing the ſame Terms in divers Senſes. Beſides, its obvious enough to imagine, that they may have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times contradicted themſelves, on a ſubject whereof they had no diſtinct Idea.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Remarks were neceſſary to prevent the queſtions which might be offer'd on theſe matters, and to ſhew that in writing the Hiſtory of theſe Doctrins, one ſhould keep wholly to Facts, and the Terms of the Authors we treat of.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Opinion of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> which has made a great noiſe in the World, is that of the Prae exiſtence of Souls, in places above the Moon,<note n="(b)">Vid. Plato's Timoeus.</note> of the faults which they may have there commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; of their baniſhment from theſe happy Abodes, to come to inhabit in differently diſpoſed Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, according to the different merits of theſe Souls; in fine, of their return into places whence they drew their Original. We ſhall not trouble our ſelves to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain this Doctrin, becauſe it belongs not to the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in hand, having only made mention of it, for a particular Reaſon which will appear in its Place.</p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> having carried the Sciences of the <hi>Greeks</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were in great numbers in theſe two Kingdoms, and who were oblig'd to converſe with them, learnt of them their Opinions; and made no difficulty of embracing thoſe, which did not appear to 'em contrary to their Religion. Their Books containing nothing inconſiſtent with ſundry of the Platonic Doctrins; they believ'd therefore, that theſe Doctrins might be true, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd them ſo much the more eaſily, in that they thought, they might hereby defend their Religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and make them relliſh it the better. <hi>Plato</hi> every where affirm'd the Unity of the ſupream
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61363:9"/>Being, yet without denying that there are other Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which may be called <hi>Gods;</hi> to wit, the Angels, which is agreeable to the Expreſſions of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. And this is apparently one of the things which made the <hi>Jews</hi> better relliſh the Opinions of this Philoſopher.</p>
            <p>But we ſhould give ſome particular Proofs of this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Author of the Book of the <hi>Wiſdom of Solomon,</hi> was plainly of the Opinion of the Prae exiſtence of Souls, as it appears from theſe Words of the viii <hi>Ch.</hi> 19, &amp; 20 verſes, <hi>For I was a witty Child, and had a good Spirit. Yea, rather being good, I came into a Body undefiled.</hi> The ſame Author has uſed the Word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in ſome places, where <hi>Plato</hi> would have uſed it, were he to have ſaid the ſame thing. Thus in the 18 <hi>ch.</hi> 15, 16, <hi>v.</hi> in ſpeaking of the Deliverer of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> he ſays, <hi>Thy Almighty Reaſon deſcended from Heaven, out of thy Royal Throne, as a fierce Man of War into the midſt of a Land of Deſtruction, and brought thine unfeigned Commandment, as a ſharp Sword, and ſtanding up, fill'd all things with Death; and it touched the Heav'n, but it ſtood upon the Earth.</hi> In the ix <hi>Ch.</hi> 1 <hi>v.</hi> He ſays, <hi>that God has made all things by his Reaſon.</hi> It cannot be alledg'd, that he has been the only one of the <hi>Jews</hi> that has ſpoke in this manner, ſeeing that <hi>Philo,</hi> who liv'd a little while after our Saviour, is full of the like Expreſſions, as ſeveral of the learned have obſerv'd. It's known that this Author has ſo well imitated <hi>Plato,</hi> that he has been call'd the <hi>Jewiſh Plato.</hi> He believ'd that there was one only ſupream God, as all the reſt of the <hi>Jews</hi> do, whom he calls, TO ON, the being through Excellency: But he far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acknowledged a Divine Nature, which he calls ΛΟΓΟΣ, the Reaſon, as well as <hi>Plato;</hi> and another whom he calls likewiſe the <hi>Soul of the World.</hi> His
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61363:10"/>Writings are ſo full of theſe manners of ſpeaking, that there is no need of offering Inſtances.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> were of theſe Opinions when our Saviour and his Apoſtles came into the World; and this is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Reaſon why we find, accordingly as it has been obſerv'd by ſeveral learned Men, ſeveral Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic Phraſes in the New Teſtament, eſpecially in the Goſpel of St. <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's well known, that <hi>Amelius</hi> the Platonic Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, having read the beginning of this Goſpel, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marked, that this Apoſtle ſpake like <hi>Plato.</hi> In effect, this Philoſopher might have ſaid, according to his Principles, <hi>The Reaſon was in the beginning with God, and was God: She it is who hath made all things, who is life, and the light of Men,</hi> &amp;c. We find ſeveral Paſſages in <hi>Philo,</hi> like to this. This Jewiſh Philoſopher calls Reaſon, the Prieſt, the Mediator between God and Men, the eldeſt Son of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein it is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he mixes his Jewiſh Notions, with the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſpeaking of <hi>Plato.</hi> He has likewiſe uſed in one Place the Term, <hi>Paraclete,</hi>
               <note n="(a)">De Vit, Moſ. p. <hi>521.</hi> Edit. Gen. Graeco. Lat</note> Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, in ſpeaking of the Reaſon: <hi>It was neceſſary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſaid he, <hi>that the High Prieſt who is to offer Sacrifices to the Father of the World ſhould have for Interceſſour — him of his Sons, whoſe Vertue is the moſt perfect, for to obtain the pardon of Sins, and abundant Graces.</hi> He had ſaid,<note n="(b)">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uod det. pot. inſid. p. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Moſes</hi> denoted by the <hi>Manna,</hi> and by the <hi>Rock</hi> of the Deſert, the ſame Reaſon: <hi>The Prophet,</hi> ſays he, <hi>calls elſewhere this Rock Manna, a name which ſignifies the ſame thing, to wit, the Divine Reaſon, the moſt ancient of Beings.</hi> Our Saviour Chriſt calls himſelf in St. John, <hi>Paraclete,</hi> ch. xiv 16. when he promiſes his Apoſtles to ſend them <hi>another Paraclete;</hi> he ſays likewiſe, that he is the <hi>true
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61363:10"/>Bread,</hi> in oppoſition to the Manna, which cou'd be no more than a ſhadow of it; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, That the Stone of the Deſert <hi>was Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. Theſe ways of ſpeaking which are found in St. <hi>John, to be the true Bread, the true Vine,</hi> and which denote, that he to whom they are applied, is able to produce in mens Spirits as much efficacy, in another kind of things, as the Bread and Wine produce in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; theſe ways of ſpeaking, I ſay, were particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to the Platoniſts, as has been obſerved elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
            <p>We might give ſeveral other Examples of Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic Phraſes, to be met with in the New Teſtament; but it will be ſufficient to remark here, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles apply to our Savior Chriſt Paſſages of the Old Teſtament, which <hi>Philo</hi> had applied to the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and that this Jewiſh Philoſopher has giv'n to this ſame Reaſon moſt of the Titles which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles have giv'n to Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Pagans,</hi> who had then embraced the Goſpel, and who were in ſome meaſure verſt in the Heathen Philoſophy, remarking this reſemblance of Terms, perſwaded themſelves, that the Apoſtles believ'd the ſame things, in reſpect of theſe matters, as the Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans.</hi> And this ſeems to be that which drew ſeveral Philoſophers of this Sect into the Chriſtian Religion, and giv'n ſuch a great eſteem to the Primitive Chriſtians, for <hi>Plato: Juſtin Martyr,</hi> in his firſt Apology, ſays, that<note n="(a)">P. <hi>48.</hi> Ed. Col. An. <hi>1686.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt was known in part by</hi> Socrates; <hi>for the Reaſon was and is ſtill the ſame, which is in every man. It is ſhe that has foretold the future by the Prophets, and who being become ſubject to the ſame Infirmities as we, has inſtructed us by her ſelf.</hi> He
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61363:11"/>ſays moreover,<note n="(b)">P. <hi>51.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſ. ed.</note> 
               <hi>That the Opinions of</hi> Plato, <hi>are not remote from thoſe of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And this has made likewiſe St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> to ſay, <hi>That if the ancient Platoniſts were ſuch as they were deſcribed, and were to riſe again, they would freely embrace Chriſtianity, in changing</hi>
               <note n="(c)">De Ver. Rel. c. <hi>3.</hi> Vid. &amp; Ep. IVl.</note> 
               <hi>ſome few Words and Opinions,</hi> which moſt of the late Platoniſts, and thoſe of his time have done, <hi>paucis mutatis verbis at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſententiis, Chriſtiani fierent, ſicut pleri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recentiorum, noſtrorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> temporum Platonici fecerunt. Tertullian</hi> affirms in his Apology,<note n="(a)">C. XXI.</note> that when the Chriſtians ſay, That <hi>God has made the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe by his Word, by his Reaſon, and by his Power, they ſpeak only after the ſage Heathens, who tell us, That God has made the World by his</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Word or Reaſon. Clement Alexandrin</hi> has likewiſe believ'd, that <hi>Plato</hi> held the Doctrin of the bleſſed Trinity. <hi>Origen</hi> againſt <hi>Celſus</hi> does not deny, but that <hi>Plato</hi> ſpake the truth, in ſpeaking of God,<note n="(b)">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 6 <hi>p.</hi> 276, &amp; 280.</note> and of his Son; he only maintains, that he did not make ſuch a juſt uſe as he ought of his Knowledge. He does not ſay, that the Foundation of the Chriſtian Doctrin is different in this from that of <hi>Plato,</hi> but that this Philoſopher had learnt it from the Jews. <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> in his harangue to the Saints,<note n="(c)">Cap. IX.</note> after having prais'd <hi>Plato,</hi> in that he was the firſt Philoſopher, who brought men to the contemplation of intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual things, thus goes on: <hi>He has ſpoken of a firſt God, who is above all Eſſences, wherein he has done well. He has likewiſe ſubmitted to him a Second, and has diſtinguiſht two Eſſences in number,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>the Perfection of the one being the ſame as that of the other, and the Eſſence of the ſecond God taking
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61363:11"/>his Exiſtence from the firſt. For it is he who is the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and the Director of all things, being above all. He that is after him, having executed his Orders, attributes to him, as to the ſupream cauſe, the production of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. There is then but one, to ſpeak properly, who takes care and provides for all, to wit, the Reaſon, who is God, and who has ſet all things in their order. This Reaſon being God, is likewiſe the Son of God; for who can call him otherwiſe, without committing a great fault? He that is the Father of all things, is juſtly ſaid to be the Father of his own proper Reaſon.</hi> HI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THERTO <hi>PLATO</hi> HAS SPOKE LIKE A WISE MAN, (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>but he has varied from the truth, in introducing a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of Gods, and in giving to each of 'em his form.</hi> We might cite ſeveral other ſuch like Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whereby one might ſee, that ſeveral among the Fathers of the firſt three Centuries have believ'd, that the Opinion of <hi>Plato</hi> and that of the Apoſtles was the ſame.</p>
            <p>If we conſider, that the Queſtion here is about things of which we have naturally no <hi>Idea,</hi> and which is even incomprehenſible, ſuppoſing revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and of which one can only ſpeak in metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical and improper Language, it will then appear to us no wonder, if ſince the Apoſtles times, there have aroſe ſeveral Opinions on this Subject. Thus the <hi>Ebionites</hi> are charged, to have denied the Prae-exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of our Savior's Divinity, and to have held, that he was only a meer Man. Theſe <hi>Ebionites</hi> have remain'd a long time, ſeeing that not only <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> and St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> do mention them, but St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> ſeems to take notice, that they were in his time. It's affirm'd, That <hi>Artemon,</hi> under the Emperor <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus</hi> and <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61363:12"/>the Emperor <hi>Aurelius,</hi> maintain'd the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> on the contrary, held the Prae-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence of the Reaſon, which he call'd the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and affirm'd, that ſhe had deſcended on Jeſus, in the form of a Dove, when he was Baptiz'd, and that ſhe aſcended up into Heaven, when he was crucifi'd. It is indeed very difficult to affirm, that this was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely the Opinions of theſe Hereticks, becauſe we have nothing remaining to us of them, and that we cannot fully truſt thoſe who ſpeak of 'em only with deteſtation, ſeeing it might eaſily be, that their great Zeal has hindred them from well comprehending them. And this is a Remark which we muſt make in reſpect of all the ancient Hereticks, whoſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions are denoted to us only from the Writings of their Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>About the middle of the third Century, <hi>Sabellius</hi> produced a new Opinion, which was condemned in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and afterwards every where. He was charg'd with<note n="(a)">Synod. Conſt. ap The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. lib. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Damaſcus apud cundem, c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>confounding the Hypoſtaſis, and denying the Properties</hi> which diſtinguiſh the Father, the Son, and Holy Ghoſt, and for having ſaid, <hi>that the Father is the ſame as the Son.</hi> Whereas <hi>Plato</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers reckoned three numerical Eſſences. It ſeems, that <hi>Sabellius</hi> wou'd acknowledge but one, whom he call'd the Father, the Son, or Holy Spirit in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers regards. It's ſaid, that ſome others had main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd the ſame thing before and after him, as <hi>Noet</hi> and <hi>Beryllus</hi> of <hi>Botſra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A while after <hi>Sabellius,</hi> appear'd <hi>Paulus Samoſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who was, as we have ſaid, of the <hi>Ebionites</hi> Sentiment, in relation to our Savior's Divinity. Altho' the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> had been uſed in the Platonic Philoſophy, to ſignifie what is of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61363:12"/>ſame kind, as has been obſerv'd already, and as may be ſeen in <hi>Bull's Defence.</hi> Nicene Council, <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>ch.</hi> 1. Yet the Council which met at <hi>Antioch,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatia,</hi> condemn'd likewiſe this term. But it's hard to find in what ſenſe it was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, becauſe the Acts of this Council are loſt, and we know nothing of them, but by what St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and ſome others extreamly intereſſed to uphold this word, have ſaid in their Diſputes againſt the <hi>Arians.</hi> If we believe them, the Fathers of the Council of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſaid, that the Father and the Son were not <hi>conſubſtantial,</hi> in the ſame ſenſe wherein we ſay, that two pieces of Mony made of the ſame Metal are <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial,</hi> becauſe that theſe pieces ſuppoſe a prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent matter, of which they have been both form'd; whereas the Father and the Son do not ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the like ſubſtance. <hi>Paulus Somoſatenus</hi> ſaid, that if the Son had not been made God, we muſt ſuppoſe, that he is of the ſame kind of effence as that of the Father; and that thus there muſt have been an anterior ſubſtance to the one and to the other, of which they muſt have been form'd. St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> aſſures us,<note n="(a)">
                  <hi>In</hi> lib. de Syn. Arim. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Seleue. II. p. <hi>919.</hi> Seq.</note> that the term of <hi>homoouſios</hi> was condemn'd at <hi>Antioch,</hi> in as much only as it might include the <hi>Idea</hi> of a matter anterior to things which we call <hi>coeſſentials</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the chief heretical Opinions, touching the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, which appear'd before the Council of <hi>Nice.</hi> As for the Fathers, which are reſpected as Orthodox, they have not varied from the Expreſſions of the <hi>Platoniſts;</hi> and as theſe have ſometimes ſaid, that the Reaſon is different from the Supream Being, and ſometimes, that they are both one: The Fathers have expreſt themſelves in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61363:13"/>ſame Terms. The <hi>Platoniſts</hi> have ſaid, That the Father could not be without the Son, nor the Son without the Father; as the Light could not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Sun, nor the Sun without Light; and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſaid the ſame thing. Both one and the other have acknowledged, that the Reaſon has exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before the World, and that ſhe has produced it; and as <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaks in his <hi>Timaeus,</hi> and <hi>Plotinus</hi> in his <hi>Enneades</hi> of the Generation of Reaſon, as if the good it ſelf had produced it, to create and govern the World: So the Fathers have ſaid, that the Son hath proceeded in ſome manner from the Father, before the Creation of the World, to manifeſt himſelf to men by his Production, and that hence it is, that the Scripture calls him the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and his <hi>Firſt born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes they ſay, there was a time in which the Son was not; ſometimes, that he was from Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting as well as the Father; ſometimes they affirm, they are equal; and elſewhere they ſay, the Father is greateſt. Some of 'em believe, that the Father and Son <hi>are two Hypoſtaſes, two Natures, two Eſſences,</hi> as appears from the Paſſage of <hi>Pierius,</hi> related by<note n="(a)">Cod. CXIX.</note> 
               <hi>Photius;</hi> others deny it. To bring Inſtances of all this, would be too great an Enlargement for this Place; and there being enough to be ſeen in <hi>Bulls</hi> Book, which we have already cited.</p>
            <p>If it be demanded at preſent, what Ideas they fixt to theſe Expreſſions, it cannot be affirm'd that they have been clear: Firſt, becauſe whatever endeavours are uſed to underſtand what they ſay, a man can get no diſtinct Notion thereof; and ſecondly, becauſe they acknowledge themſelves, that it is a thing incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible. All that can be done on this occaſion, is to relate the Terms which they have uſed, to the end, that it may be ſeen, how they have heretofore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61363:13"/>themſelves on this matter. However, learned Men have given themſelves a great deal of trouble to explain the Paſſages of the Fathers, who liv'd before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> without conſidering, that all their Explications are fruitleſs, ſeeing the Fathers, in acknowledging that what they ſaid was incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, acknowledged at the ſame time, that they fix'd no Idea on the Terms they uſed, unleſs ſuch as were general and confuſed.</p>
            <p>Had the matter ſtaid here, there had never been ſuch great Diſputes on the Sentiments of the Ancients, touching this Myſtery, ſeeing the Diſpute doth not ſo much lie on the Terms they have uſed, as the Ideas they have faſtned to them, which cannot be reduced to any thing that is clear. Sometimes they uſe Terms, which ſeem perfectly to agree with thoſe which have been uſed ſince; but there is found in ſome other places of their Works, Expreſſions which ſeem to overthrow what they had ſaid, ſo that one cannot form any Notion of what they thought. <hi>Lactantius,</hi> for Example, anſwers thus to the Heathens, who ask'd the Chriſtians, how they ſaid they acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but one God, ſeeing they gave this Name to the Father, and to the Son?<note n="(a)">Inſtit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>29.</hi> pag. <hi>403.</hi> Ed. Oxon.</note> 
               <hi>When we call the Father God, and the Son God, we do not ſay, that each of them is a different God; and we do not ſeparate them; becauſe the Father cannot be without the Son, nor the Son ſeparated from the Father: He cannot be called Father, without his Son, nor the Son be begotten without his Father. Seeing then that the Father makes the Son, and that the Son is made; the one and the other has the ſame Intellect, one only Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and one only Subſtance; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TRIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E MENS, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S SPIRIT <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>B<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTIA.</hi> Theſe are Words which ſeem to be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61363:14"/>deciſive; and had <hi>Lactantius</hi> held to theſe Expreſſions, he had never been accuſed of Heterodoxy; but if he be queſtion'd what he means by the Word <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus,</hi> whether it be a <hi>Numerical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Conſent and Reſemblance,</hi> he will appear determin'd to this latter Senſe:<note n="(a)">Ib. p. <hi>404.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When any one,</hi> ſays he, <hi>has a Son whom he dearly loves, and who dwells in the Houſe, and under the governing Power of his Father, although the Father grants him the Name and Authority of a Maſter; yet in the Terms of Civilians, here is but one Houſe and one Maſter. So this World is but one Houſe belonging to God, and the Son and the Father who inhabit the World, and who are of one Mind,</hi> (Unanimes) <hi>are one only God, the one being as the two, and the two as the one. And this ought not to appear ſtrange, ſeeing the Son is in the Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Father loveth the Son, and the Father is in the Son, by reaſon of his faithful Reſignation to his Fathers Will; and that he does nothing, nor ever did do any thing, unleſs what the Father has will'd, or commanded him.</hi> We may read farther, the vi. Ch. of the iv. Book, which begins thus: <hi>God who has conceiv'd and produced all Things, before he began this curious work of the World, begat a Spirit Holy and Incorruptible, that he might call him his Son. Although he has produced infinite others, whom we call Angels, for his Miniſtry, yet has he vouchſafed to give the Name of Son to his only Firſt-born, who is cloathed with the Vertue and Majeſty of his Father.</hi> That which is particular in this, is, that though <hi>Lactantius</hi> ſays, that the Son is Co-eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal with the Father, yet he ſays, there was a time when he was not.<note n="(a)">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> in Ed. Betuleij.</note> 
               <hi>Sicut mater ſine exemplo genuit auctorem ſuum; ſic ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter Pater genuiſſe credendus eſt Co aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. De Matre natus eſt qui ante jam fuit; de Patre
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61363:14"/>qui aliquando non fuit. Hoc fides credat, intelligentia non requirat, ne aut non inventum putet incredibile, aut repertum non credat ſingulare.</hi> It's true, this Paſſage is not to be found in ſome Manuſcripts, and that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral learned men have fancied, that ſome ſly Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick has corrupted <hi>Lactantius</hi> Works: but in other places, wherein all the Manuſcripts do agree, <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> expreſſes himſelf after the ſame manner; and it may be replied with as much likelihood, that it has been the Orthodox Reviſors who have cut off what they thought not fit to be made publick. <hi>Lactantius</hi> has been long ſince charg'd with Heterodoxy; but in this reſpect, he has been no more faulty than other Fathers, who liv'd before the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> whoſe Expreſſions are as different as thoſe of the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> in matter of the Trinity. And this has made Father <hi>Peteau</hi> and Mr. <hi>Huet,</hi> to charge them with favoring the <hi>Arian</hi> Sentiments, whilſt other learned Men have maintain'd, that they have been far from them. Each of them cites his Paſſages, which examin'd a-part, ſeem to decide for him: But when one comes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare theſe Paſſages with one another; it cannot be comprehended how the ſame Perſons could ſpeak ſo differently. In this Compariſon, their Expreſſions are found ſo obſcure, and ſo full of apparent Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or real ones, that a man feels himſelf oblig'd to believe, That the Fathers had done a great deal better in keeping themſelves to the Terms of the Apoſtles, and to have acknowledged, that they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood them not, than to throw themſelves into ſuch Labyrinths, by endeavouring to explain them.</p>
            <p>To ſhew farther, that the Expreſſions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are only fit to produce confuſed Notions, and ſuch as are contrary to thoſe, which all Chriſtians at this day hold; we need only read <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61363:15"/>having ſaid in his Apology, <hi>Ch.</hi> xxi. That the Nature of Reaſon is ſpiritual; adds, <hi>Hunc ex Deo prolatum didicimus, &amp; prolatione Generatum &amp; idcirco Filium, &amp; Deum dictum ex unitate ſubſtantiae, nam &amp; Deus Spiritus eſt:</hi> But what means <hi>Prolatum genitus?</hi> The Terms of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Subſtance,</hi> may ſignifie, not only of the ſame Subſtance <hi>in Number,</hi> but moreover, of a like Subſtance, that is to ſay, ſpiritual and equally perfect: And what he adds, ſeems to favour this laſt ſenſe; <hi>Etiam cum radius ex ſole porrigitur, portio ex ſumma, ſed Sol erit in radio, quia Solis eſt radius; nec ſeparatur ſubſtantia, ſed extenditur.</hi> The ſubſtance of a Ray, after what manner ſoever we conceive it, is not the ſame <hi>in Number</hi> as that of the Sun; and <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſays, that it is the ſame of the Son. <hi>Ita de Spiritu Spiritus, &amp; de Deo Deus;</hi> Thus a Spirit is born of a Spirit, and a God of a God. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Lumen de lumine accenditur, manet integra, &amp; indefecta materiae matrix, etſi plures inde traduces qualitatum mutueris;</hi> as when we light one Torch by another, the Light which has lighted the other, remains entire and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being waſted, although we light ſeveral Torches, who have the ſame qualities. <hi>Ita &amp; quod de Deo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum eſt, Deus eſt, &amp; Dei filius &amp; unus ambo. Ita de Spiritu Spiritus, &amp; de Deo Deus modulo alternum numerum gradu, non ſtatu fecit, &amp; à matrice non receſſit, ſed exceſſit:</hi> So what proceeds from God is God, and Son of God, and both are but one; ſo the Spirit which is born of a Spirit, and the God who is born of a God, makes two in reſpect of Degree, but not in reſpect of his State; he has not been ſeparated from the Womb, or from his Original, but is gone out of it.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:61363:15"/>
            <p>Theſe Words of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> do not appear at firſt ſight agreeable with <hi>Arius</hi>'s Opinion; but at moſt, they contain nothing that is clear, for one might have demanded of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> whether by this <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> he ſpeaks of, the Reaſon has exiſted as Light from a Torch, lighted by another Torch exiſts, as ſoon as it is lighted? Should he allow it, he might have been told, that to ſpeak ſtrictly, there muſt then have been two Gods, ſeeing that, in fine, two Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, though exactly equal, and ſtrictly united, are two Spirits. If this be ſo, the ſecond Spirit being not form'd of the ſame numerical Subſtance, as that of the firſt, one might ſay with <hi>Arius,</hi> that he has been <hi>extracted from nothing;</hi> and there would be in this regard, nothing but a Diſpute about Words, between <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Tertullian.</hi> But if it be anſwer'd for <hi>Tertullian,</hi> that his compariſon is not good, it will be ask'd, why he made uſe of a compariſon which may lead into Errour, eſpecially having ſaid before, that he was of <hi>Plato</hi>'s opinion touching the Reaſon? If he meant, that the Father has produced in his proper Subſtance, without multiplying it, <hi>a Modifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> in reſpect of which, one may call the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Father, Son; why does he ſay, <hi>Spiritus ex Spiritu, ex Deo, Deus?</hi> For to ſpeak properly, the Father has produced neither a Spirit, nor a God, but a new manner of being in his proper Subſtance.</p>
            <p>It is farther to be obſerved, that this Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not of <hi>Tertullian</hi> alone, but of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and a great number of Fathers beſides, before and after the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> and that there is no Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage which appears of greater force than that, yet the Equivocation of it is apparent.</p>
            <p>The Fathers have likewiſe uſed the Term <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis,</hi> as well as the <hi>Platoniſts,</hi> in two ſenſes; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61363:16"/>for the Exiſtence taken in an abſtracted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and ſometimes for the thing it ſelf, which exiſts. The Equivocation of this Term, and that of the Words, <hi>One and Many,</hi> which, as has been ſhew'd, are taken ſometimes from the Unity, and the Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality <hi>Specificals,</hi> and ſometimes from the Unity and Plurality <hi>Numericals,</hi> have caus'd great Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies among the Fathers, as divers learned Men have<note n="a">(a) Petavius, Curcellaeus, Huetius, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> obſerv'd. But it is fit we ſhould take notice of one thing, which is, that <hi>Bull</hi> who has writ Prolixly on this matter, has not a word of the <hi>Numerical</hi> and <hi>Specific <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> without which, a man cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what the Fathers mean, nor draw any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions from them againſt the Hereticks. Yet when they ſay there are <hi>three Hypoſtaſes,</hi> or <hi>three Eſſences,</hi> or <hi>three Natures,</hi> he conſtantly takes it as if they ſaid, there are three Modifications in one only Numerical Eſſence. He ſuppoſes, that the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Nature,</hi> ſignifie manners of exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one Numerical Eſſence, only becauſe that without this, thoſe who have thus ſpoken of it, would not have been Orthodox, or of the Opinion at preſent receiv'd, which the Council muſt have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd of, ſeeing other wiſe it would not have been admitted as it is. He ſuppoſes on the contrary, for the ſame Reaſons, that when the Fathers deny there are three <hi>Hypoſtaſes,</hi> they do not barely mean, that there are not three Eſſences of different kinds, but that there are not three in number. But others will deny there is any place, where the Words <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Eſſence</hi> can be taken for what we at this day call <hi>Perſonality,</hi> which is to ſay, for a Modification; and that it appears from the Paſſages which he cites, that the Fathers held the <hi>Numerical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:61363:16"/>
            <p>And this was the condition of the Chriſtian Church, when the quarrels of <hi>Arius</hi> diſturb'd it; Whence may be ſeen, that it was no hard matter for the two Parties to cite Authorities of the Ancients, whoſe Equivocal Expreſſions might be interpreted in divers Senſes. The Obſcurity of the Subject, the vain Subtilty of humane Underſtanding, which would know every thing, the Deſire of appearing able, and the Paſſion which mingles it ſelf in all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, gave Birth to theſe Controverſies, which for a long time tore Chriſtianity into pieces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius</hi> being a Prieſt of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> about the year 3 8, undertook, as it ſeems, to explain more clearly, the Doctrin of the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt, which had been till that time taught in the Chriſtian Church, under the Veil of thoſe Terms which we have recit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He ſaid, that to <hi>beget</hi> in this Subject, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but to <hi>produce;</hi> whence he concluded, that the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt had been extracted out of nothing by the Father. Here's how he expreſſes himſelf, in a Letter which he wrote to <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nicomedia: We make Profeſſion to</hi>
               <note n="a">(a) Ap Theod. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>believe, that the Son is not without Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that he is not a part of that which is unbegotten, nor of any other Pre exiſtent matter what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; but that by the Will and Council</hi> (of God) <hi>he has been perfect God,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>before all Time and Ages; that he is his only Son, and that he is not ſubject to change; that before he was begotten or created, he was not. Arius</hi> was counted an able Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician,<note n="b">(b) Sozo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> and was in good eſteem with his Biſhop <hi>Alexander;</hi> but ſpeaking free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his mind, he drew on him the hatred of one <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lece</hi>
               <note n="c">(c) Epiphan. in Haet. LXIX.</note> Biſhop in <hi>Thebaida,</hi> who had caus'd a Schiſm in <hi>Egypt,</hi> although he did
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61363:17"/>not much vary from the common Opinions; only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not receive into Communion the Prieſts who had fall'n in the <hi>Diocleſian</hi> Perſecution, but after a long Pennance, and would have them for ever depriv'd of their Office.</p>
            <p>One may ſay, the Hiſtory of this in St. <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who accuſes him for having an affected Devotion, and taking up a particular way of living to make himſelf admired by the People. <hi>Arius</hi> had moreover ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Enemy, named <hi>Alexander,</hi> and Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named<note n="a">(a) Philoſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baucalas,</hi> who was alſo an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociate Prieſt with him. He joyned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Melece,</hi> to complain to the Biſhop of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> that <hi>Arius</hi> ſowed a new Doctrin touching the Divinity of our Saviour Chriſt. He could the better ſpread his Opinions, in that having a particular Church at <hi>Alexandria</hi> committed to his Care, He preach'd there what he thought fit.<note n="b">(b) Epiph. Sozom.</note> He drew ſuch a great number of People into his Opinions, that there were 700 Religious Votaries who had embraced them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, a greater number among the ordinary People. It's ſaid, that he was a man of large ſhape, of a ſevere Countenance, yet of a very agreeable Converſation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> thought, that in a matter wherein one might eaſily equivocate, it were beſt to let the two Parties explain themſelves, to the end it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that he had accorded them more by Perſwaſion than Force. He brought the two Parties to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, in demanding of them, the Explication of a Paſſage of Scripture in the Preſence of the Clergy of his Church; but neither one nor the other of theſe Parties would yield, endeavouring only to vanquiſh. <hi>Arius</hi> his Advenſaries maintained, that the Son is of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61363:17"/>the ſame eſſence (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) as the Father, and that he is eternal as he is; and <hi>Arius</hi> pretended that the generation denoted a beginning. There was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meeting called, as fruileſs as the firſt, in reſpect of the diſpute; but by which it ſeems <hi>Alexander,</hi> who had before not any preciſe determined ſentiment on this matter, was induced to embrace the opinion of <hi>Arius</hi> his adverſaries. He afterwards commanded this Prieſt <hi>to believe</hi> the ſame thing (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and to abandon the oppoſite opinion.</p>
            <p>But it being ſeldom known that Men yield obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to theſe kind of Injunctions, <hi>Arius</hi> remained ſtill in the ſame opinion, as well as ſeveral other Biſhops and Eccleſiaſtics who had approved of it. <hi>Alexander</hi> angry at his not being obey'd, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated him, with all thoſe of his party, and oblig'd him to depart out of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> There were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others, five Prieſts of this City, and as many Deacons of the ſame Church, beſides ſome Biſhops of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as <hi>Secondus</hi> and <hi>Theonas,</hi> To them were joyned a great number of People, ſome of which did in effect approve the doctrin of <hi>Arius,</hi> and others thought that he had been condemned with too high an hand, without entring into the diſcuſſion of the controverſy. After this ſeverity, the two Parties endeavoured to make their opinions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct be approved by Letters which they ſent every where. They expoſed not only their reaſons, but endeavoured to render odious the oppoſite Party, by the conſequences they drew from their opinions, and in attributing to them ſtrange expreſſions. Some Biſhops, as <hi>Euſbius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> exhorted <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> to reconcile himſelf with <hi>Arius;</hi> and others approv'd his Conduct, and adviſed him not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him into communion till he retracted. The
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61363:18"/>letters of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arius</hi> are too conſiderable to be diſregarded; Here's then the ſum of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius</hi> wrote to<note n="(a)">ap. Ephiph. in Heſ. LXIX. &amp; Theodor. lib. <hi>1.</hi> C. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <q>
                  <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat his Protection againſt <hi>Alexander</hi> who had excommunicated him and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him out of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> becauſe he could not grant him, that the Father and the Son are coeternal; that the Son coexiſts with the Father without generation, having been always begotten, and not begotten at the ſame time, without letting it be imagined that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has exiſted ſo much as one moment before the Son.</q> He added, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarea, Theodotus</hi> of <hi>Laodicea, Paulinus</hi> of <hi>Tyre, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> of <hi>Anazarba, Gregory</hi> of <hi>Beryta,</hi> and <hi>Aetius</hi> of <hi>Lydia,</hi> condemning the ſentiments of <hi>Alexander,</hi> had been likewiſe ſtruck with an Anathema, as well as all the eaſtern People who were of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, except <hi>Philogonius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>antiach, Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanicus</hi> of <hi>Tripoly,</hi> and <hi>Macarias</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> one of which ſaid that the Son <q>was an <hi>Eruclation,</hi> the other a <hi>Projection,</hi> and the other that he was not begotten, no more than the Father. To this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> added the explanation of his opinion, which we have already related.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhop<note n="(a)">Sozom. II.</note> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> having receiv'd this Letter call'd a Synod of his province of <hi>Bythinia,</hi> which wrote circular Letters to all the Eaſtern Biſhops to induce them to receive <hi>Arius</hi> into communion, as maintaining the truth, and to engage <hi>Alexander</hi> to do as much. We have ſtill a Letter of <hi>Euſebius</hi> to <hi>Paulinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tyre,</hi> wherein he not only entreats <hi>Paulinus</hi> to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed for <hi>Arius;</hi> but wherein he expoſes and defends his ſentiments with great clearneſs. He ſays <hi>he has
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61363:18"/>never heard there were two Beings without Generation, nor that the one has been parted into two, but that this ſingle Being had begotten another, not of his Subſtance, but perfectly like to him, although of a different Nature and Power; That not only we cannot expreſs by Words the beginning of the Son, but that it is even incomprehenſible to thoſe intellectual Beings, which are above men, as well as to us. To prove this, he cites the</hi> 8th <hi>of the</hi> Proverbs, God the Lord poſſeſs'd me in the beginning of his Ways, before his Works of old, I was ſet up from Everlaſting, and he has begotten me before the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains were brought forth. <hi>He ſays, that we muſt not ſearch into the Term of</hi> Begetting <hi>any other Signification than that of</hi> Producing, <hi>becauſe the Scripture does not only uſe it in Reference to the Son, but moreover, in ſpeaking of Creatures;</hi> as when God ſays, I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Children; and I have brought them up, but they have rebelled againſt me.</p>
            <p>But theſe Letters not having had the Succeſs which <hi>Arius</hi> expected, he ſent to get leave of <hi>Paulinus,</hi> of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and <hi>Patrophilus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Scythopolis,</hi> to gather thoſe who were of his Opinion into a Church, and to exerciſe among them the Office of a Prieſt, as he was want to do before, and as was done at <hi>Alexandria.</hi> Theſe Biſhops having Convocated the other Biſhops of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> granted him what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, but ordered him however to remain ſubject to <hi>Alexander,</hi> and to omit nothing to obtain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him.</p>
            <p>There is extant a Letter of <hi>Arius,</hi> directed to this Biſhop,<note n="(a)">Apud Epiph. II.</note> and written from <hi>Nicodemia,</hi> which contains a Confeſſion of Faith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Doctrin which <hi>Arius</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd that <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf had taught him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, after having denoted his Belief touching the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61363:19"/>which includes nothing Heterodox; he adds, <hi>That he hath begotten his only Son before the times Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; that it is by him, that he has made the World; that he has begotten him, not only in Appearance, but in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality; that this Son ſubſiſts by his own Will; that he is unmoveable; that he is a Creature of God that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and not as other Creatures; that he is a Production, but not as other Productions; nor as</hi> Valentinian <hi>ſaid, a</hi> Projection <hi>of the Father; nor as</hi> Manes <hi>affirm'd, a</hi> Conſubſtantial Part <hi>of the Father; nor as</hi> Sabellius <hi>called him, a</hi> Son Father; (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>nor as</hi> Hieracas <hi>ſpake, a Lamp lighted by a Lamp, or a Torch divided into two; That he did not exiſt before he was begotten, and became a Son; that there are three</hi> Hypoſtaſes <hi>(that is to ſay, different Subſtances) the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit; and that the Father is before the Son, although the Son was created before all Ages.</hi> Arius <hi>adds, That</hi> Alexander <hi>had ſeveral times preach'd this Doctrin in the Church, and refuted thoſe who did not receive it. This Letter is Sign'd by ſix Prieſts, ſeven Deacons, and three Biſhops,</hi> Secondus <hi>of</hi> Pentapolis, Theonas <hi>of</hi> Lybia, <hi>and</hi> Piſtus <hi>whom the</hi> Arian <hi>Biſhops had Eſtabliſht at</hi> Alexandria.</p>
            <p>Alexander<note n="(a)">Socrat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>wrote on his ſide circular Letters, wherein he ſharply cenſures</hi> Euſebius <hi>of</hi> Nicomedia, <hi>in that he protected</hi> Arius, <hi>and recomended him to others. He joyns to this the Names of thoſe who had been Excommunicated, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains their Doctrin, wherein he contents not himſelf to ſet down what we have ſeen in</hi> Arius <hi>Letters, touching the beginning which he attributes to the Son; he ſays moreover that this Prieſt maintain'd that the Son is one of the Creatures, that we cannot call him the Reaſon and Wiſdom of the Father but improperly, ſeeing that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has been produced by the Reaſon and Wiſdom of God;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61363:19"/>that he is ſubject to change, as other intelligent creatures; that he is of another Eſſence than God; that the Father is incomprehenſible to him, and that he knows not himſelf what is his proper ſubſtance; that he has been made for our ſakes, to ſerve God as an Inſtrument in creating us, and that without this, God had never begotten him</hi> Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander adds, <hi>That having aſſembled near an hundred Biſhops of</hi> Egypt <hi>and</hi> Lybia, <hi>they had Excommunicated</hi> Arius <hi>and his Followers, by reaſon of his Opinions.</hi> He afterwards comes to prove his, and ſhews
<list>
                  <item>firſt, <hi>The Eternity of the Son by this Paſſage of St. John,</hi> In the Beginning was the Reaſon.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That he cannot be reckoned among the Creatures; becauſe the Father ſays of him in the</hi> 45. <hi>Pſ.</hi> My heart has uttered <hi>(eructavit)</hi> a good Word.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>That he is not unlike the Eſſence of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of which he is the perfect Image, and the</hi> Splendor, <hi>and of whom he ſays,</hi> He that has ſeen me, has ſeen the Father.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>That we cannot ſay, there was a time in which he was not, ſeeing that he is the Reaſon, and the Wiſdom of the Father; and that it will be abſurd to ſay, there was a time in which the Father was without Reaſon and Wiſdom.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>That he is not ſubject to change, becauſe the Scripture ſays,</hi> He is the ſame yeſterday and to day.</item>
                  <item>6. That he was not made becauſe of us, <hi>ſeeing St.</hi> Paul <hi>ſays, that it is</hi> becauſe of him, and by him that all things are.</item>
                  <item>7. <hi>That the Father is not incomprehenſible to the Son, ſeeing he ſays,</hi> As the Father knows me, ſo I know the Father.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>This Letter wherein <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ill treated, ſhockt this Biſhop to the utmoſt Point, and having great acceſs to the Court, becauſe <hi>Conſtantine</hi> made then his abode at <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> this occaſion'd divers Biſhops to be at his Devotion; but he could not engage <hi>Alexander</hi> to forget what had paſt, to ſpeak no more of this Controverſie, and to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61363:20"/>receive <hi>Arius</hi> into Communion. The quarrels every day grew hotter, and the People were ſeen to range themſelves, ſome taking <hi>Arius</hi> ſide, others <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders;</hi> and the <hi>Comedians</hi> being Gentiles, this gave them occaſion to make a Sport of Chriſtian Religion on their Theaters.</p>
            <p>Each ſide treated one another with the odious Name of Heretick, and endeavour'd to ſhew, that the Sentiments of the oppoſite Party overthrew the Chriſtian Religion; but it appears, that neither the one, nor the other Party, could yet perſwade the Emperor, ſeeing he wrote to <hi>Alexander</hi> and to <hi>Arius,</hi> a long Letter, of which <hi>Hoſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cordovia</hi> was the bearer, wherein he equally chides them: He ſays, he found that the Controverſie<note n="(a)">Apud Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. de vit. Conſt. cap. <hi>64.</hi> &amp; Seq. &amp; So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> had begun in this manner; That <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> having demanded of each of his Prieſts, what they thought of a paſſage of Scripture, or rather, <hi>on an idle ſort of Question?</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Arius</hi> inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately anſwer'd what he ſhould have thought, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conceal'd, if he had thought it, <q>That from thence had come his Excommunication, and the Diviſion of the People. And therefore, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to a mutual pardoning of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to receive his Opinion, which was, That it had been better not to have troubled the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks with this Queſtion; and that thoſe who were ask'd it, ſhould have held their Tongues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter concern'd what was equally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible to both Parties, and which ſerv'd only to raiſe Diſturbances among the People. He could not conceive, how for a Queſtion of very ſmall Importance, and in which, if they well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood one another, they would find they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61363:20"/>agreed in the main, they ſhould make ſuch a buſtle, and divide themſelves in ſo ſcandalous a manner.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do not ſay this,</hi> adds he, <hi>as if I would conſtrain you to think the ſame thing on a moſt vain Queſtion, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you will pleaſe to call it. For one may without diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring the Aſſembly, and without breaking the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, be in different Sentiments in ſuch inconſiderable things. We have not all the ſame Wills in all things, neither are we all of us of the ſame temper of Body and Humors. The Emperors Letter,</hi> ſays Socrates, <hi>gave them admirable Advice, and full of Wiſdom; but the Miſchief was grown too great, and neither the Emperors Endeavours, nor his Authority, who brought the Letter to</hi> Alexandria, <hi>could appeaſe it. Alexander</hi> had taken care to write every where, to hinder the ſpreading of <hi>Arius</hi> his Opinions. We have ſtill a long Letter which he wrote to the Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wherein he vehemently inveighs againſt the <hi>Arian</hi> Faction, and endeavours to render it odious; in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That</hi> Arius <hi>maintain'd, that the Son was of a Nature capable of evil as well as of good, although it actually remain'd without ſin, and that it was for this, that God had choſen him for his eldeſt Son. He proves the Eternity of the Son, and that he was not extracted from nothing, becauſe he was in the beginning, and that all things have been made by him. Yet he holds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the Son has been begotten, and that only the Father is without Generation, although that the</hi> Subſiſtence, <hi>or</hi> Subſtance <hi>of the Son,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>be incomprehenſible to the Angels themſelves, and that there is none but melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Perſons who can think of comprehending it. He afterwards ſhews, that the manner after which Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God, is infinitely more excellent than the manner after which Men are, ſeeing he is ſo by his Nature, we only by Adoption.</hi> He accuſes <hi>Arius</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:61363:21"/>with following the Doctrin of <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Artemas,</hi> and for having imitated <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatia,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> whoſe Doctrin had been embraced by <hi>Lucien,</hi> (Martyr) who by reaſon of this, had ſeparated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Communion of three following Biſhops of this City. He joyns to him three Biſhops of <hi>Syria,</hi> who ſeem to have been, <hi>Paulinus, Euſebius,</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus,</hi> and reproaches them with uſing Paſſages, which relate to the Humiliation of Chriſt, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack his Divinity, and to have forgotten thoſe which ſpeak of the Glory of his Nature, ſuch as this is; <hi>The Father and I are one; which the Lord ſays,</hi> adds he, <hi>not to denote that he is the Father, nor to ſay, that two Natures, in reſpect of the manner of exiſting,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>are but one; but becauſe the Son is of a Nature, which exactly keeps the Paternal Reſemblance, being by his Nature like to him in all things, the unchangeable Image of his Father, and a Copy of this Original. He afterwards defends himſelf largely againſt the Conſequence which</hi> Arius <hi>drew from his Adverſaries Sentiments, which conſiſted in accuſing them, for denying the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Son, in making him Eternal.</hi> He affirm'd, <hi>That there is an infinite difference between the Creation, of the World, and the Generation of the Son, although this laſt be wholly incomprehenſible, and that he cannot explain it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Diviſion increaſed ſo greatly among the People, that in ſome places, it came to a Sedition, wherein the very Statues<note n="(a)">Euſeb. de vit. Conſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> of the Emperor were thrown down, who appear'd to favour the <hi>Arians,</hi> becauſe he would have 'em tolerated. There was moreover, the Controverſie about <hi>Eaſter,</hi> the one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that it ſhould be celebrated at the ſame time as the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> and the others affirming it; but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61363:21"/>this conteſt, had not produced a Schiſm, as <hi>Arianiſm</hi> had done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantin</hi> ſeeing that theſe Letters had been fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, thought there was no better way to allay theſe controverſies, than to call a Council, from all Parts of the Roman Empire. It was perhaps <hi>Hoſius</hi> who gave him this advice, at leaſt if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Philoſtorgus,</hi>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone to <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> there aſſembled ſome Biſhops of his opinion, with whom <hi>Hoſius</hi> and he conſults, to find out means to ſet up their opinion and to make that of <hi>Arius</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and a little while after the <hi>Emperor</hi> call'd a Council at <hi>Nice,</hi> a Town of <hi>Bithynia.</hi>
               <note n="(b)">Euſeb. in vit. Conſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> This was in the year 325, and to the end that nothing might hinder the Biſhops from coming, <hi>Conſtantin</hi> took on himſelf the charges of their journey. The Hiſtori ans are not agreed in reference to the number of e'm, ſome ſetting down more than 300<note n="(c)">Euſtathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us of Antioch ſays there were <hi>270.</hi> Theod. <hi>1.</hi> &amp;. Conſtantin <hi>300</hi> Socr. <hi>11.9.</hi> Euſebius <hi>250</hi> vit. Conſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> S. Athananſ. <hi>318.</hi>
               </note> and others leſs. We muſt not wonder at this diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, ſeeing there are few paſſages in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtory, wherein appears more confuſion and neglect than in the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this famous Council. And there fore have we been obliged to extract what we are going to ſay, out of divers Hiſtorians, becauſe none of the Ancients has been compleat in his relations. As to the diverſity obſervable among the Hiſtorians on the ſame facts, we have followed either the moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, or thoſe which have appeared moſt probable. <hi>Euſebius</hi> who was preſent at the Council, has paſt very lightly over the Circumſtances of this Hiſtory apparently, leſt he ſhould either offend the <hi>Arians,</hi> or
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61363:22"/>the Orthodox. This affair has never been ſince diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of with an entire diſintereſt, reports having been often related as certain facts. In a word, there has never any thing hapned, whereunto one may apply with more reaſon theſe words of <hi>Tacitus: Maxima quaeque ambigua ſunt, dum alij quoquomodo audita pro compertis habent, alij vera in contrarium veriunt, et gliſcit utrumque poſteritati. Euſebius</hi> vaunts very much of the Biſhops which were here, but <hi>Sabinus</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Socrat. l. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> a Macedonian Biſhop of <hi>Heraclea</hi> a Town of <hi>Thrace,</hi> treats them as Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſſes in his collection of Councils. There was likewiſe a great number of Prieſts and Deacons, who came in Company with the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>The Council opened the 14th. of <hi>June,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were regulated ſeveral things, which we ſhall not here take notice of, deſigning only to remark what paſt in relation to the principal queſtion therein deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, to wit <hi>Arianiſm.</hi> Aſſoon as ever the Biſhops were arrived, they made particular Aſſemblies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcountenance, and ſent for <hi>Arius</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Sozom. l. <hi>17.</hi> &amp; <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> to them to inform themſelves of his opinions. After they had heard from him what he thought, ſome of 'em were for condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all ſorts of novelties, and to content themſelves in ſpeaking of the Son, in the ſame terms their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors had uſed; and others affirm'd that the opinions of the Ancients were not to be received without examining. There were ſeventeen Biſhops according to <hi>Sozomen</hi>
               <note n="(b)">ib. cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> who favoured <hi>Arius</hi> his new explications, the chief of which were <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia, Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea, Menophantes</hi> of <hi>Epheſus, Patrophilus</hi> of <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thopolis, Theognis</hi> of <hi>Nice, Narciſſus</hi> of <hi>Neroniadas,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61363:22"/>Theonas</hi> of <hi>Marmarica,</hi> and <hi>Secondus</hi> of <hi>Ptolemeida.</hi> Theſe Biſhops drew up a Confeſſion of Faith<note n="(c)">Theoder. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> ex Athanaſio.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their ſentiments, but they had no ſooner read it in the Aſſembly, but it was cryed out upon as falſe; 'twas torn in pieces, and they were reproacht with it as Perſons who would, as they ſaid, betray the Faith and the Godhead of Chriſt, A Letter of <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> wherein he expreſt his thoughts, had the ſame lot.</p>
            <p>In fine, a Creed was undertaken to be made, wherein the opinions contrary to thoſe of <hi>Arius</hi> were eſtabliſhed. It was immediately obſerv'd that the new ways of ſpeaking which the <hi>Arians</hi> uſed, were to be condemned, <hi>That the Son had been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from nothing; that he was a Creature; that there was a time wherein he was not,</hi> &amp;c. and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Phraſes were to be uſed, ſuch as theſe; <hi>Only begotten Son, the Word, Power, Wiſdom of the Father, the brightneſs of his Glory, and character of his Power.</hi> The <hi>Arians</hi> having ſhew'd that they were ready to admit a Confeſſion expreſt in theſe terms; the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Biſhops feard leſt they ſhould expound theſe terms in an ill ſenſe. And therefore they were for adding that the Son is <hi>of the Subſtance of the Father,</hi> becauſe this is that which diſtinguiſhes the Son from the Creatures. Hereupon the <hi>Arians</hi> were askt, whether they acknowledged, <hi>That the Son is not a Creature, but the Power, the only Wiſdom and Image of the Father; that he is Eternal, and like to the Father in all things; in ſine true God.</hi> The <hi>Heterodox</hi> haven ſpoken among themſelves, believ'd that theſe expreſſions might very well agree with the notion they had of the Divinity of the Son, and denoted they were ready to receive them.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:61363:23"/>
            <p>In fine, it being obſerv'd that <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> in the Letter which was read, rejected the Term of <hi>Conſubſtantial,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) it was thought, that the Orthodox Doctrin could not be better expreſs'd, and all Equivocation excluded, than in making uſe of it; and ſo much the rather, in that the <hi>Arians</hi> ſeem'd to be afraid of it. This Circumſtance is owing to St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de fid. ad Grat. cap. ult.</note> whoſe Words are theſe: <hi>Auctor ipſorum Euſebius Nicomediae Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus, Epiſtola ſua prodidit, dicens; ſi verum inquit, Dei filium increatum dicimus, homoou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Conſubſtantialem cum Patre incipimus confiteri. Haec cum lecta eſſet Epiſtola in Concilio Nicoeno, hoc verbum in tractatu ſidei poſuerunt Patres quod viderunt Adverſariis eſſe formidini, ut tanquam evaginato ab ipſis gladio ipſum nefandae caput Haereſeos amputarent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Orthodox conceiv'd then their Sentiment, touching the Divinity of the Son in theſe Terms:<note n="(b)">Socr. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We believe in one only Lord Jeſus Christ, Son of God, only Son of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is to ſay, of the Subſtance of the Father, God, born of God, Light of Light, true God, born of the true God, begotten, not made, Conſubſtantial with the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Arians</hi> in vain complain'd, that theſe Words were not to be found in Scripture; They were told, that thoſe they were wont to uſe, were no more there neither, being wholly new; whereas it was near ſix-ſcore years ſince, that ſeveral Biſhops had uſed the Word, <hi>Conſubſtantial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fathers of the Council, during this Time, were not ſo buſied in vanquiſhing the <hi>Arians,</hi> and in making ſeveral Regulations, but that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred their private grudges. <hi>Several Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61363:23"/>ſays <hi>Sozomen,</hi>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>as if they had been aſſembled to proſecute their particular Affairs. as it commonly happens, thought this a fit time to get thoſe puniſh'd who had offended them. Each of 'em pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented Requeſts to the Emperor, wherein they accuſed one or other, and ſignified the wrong they had done them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This hapning every day, the Emperor ſet one a part in which they were every one of 'em to bring his Grievance. The day being come, the Emperor took all their Requeſts, and cauſed 'em to be thrown into the Fire, and exhorted them to a mutual Forgiveneſs, according to the Precepts of the Goſpel. He afterwards enjoyn'd them to labour in clearing up the Points of Faith, of which they were to be Judges, and a fixt day, wherein the Queſtion of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiality ſhould be decided.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day appointed<note n="(a)">Euſeb. vit. Conſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> being come, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> convocated all the Biſhops into an Hall of the Palace, where he had caus'd Chairs to be ſet on both ſides. The Biſhops entred firſt, and the Emperor came in afterwards, and did not ſit down at the Head of the Aſſembly on a gilded Seat, which he cauſed to be there placed, till the Biſhops, by Signs had giv'n him leave. Being ſet down, <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> who was at his Right Hand, harang'd him, and thank'd him, for the care he had taken to preſerve the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Catholick Faith. <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> afterwards began to ſpeak, and made a Diſcourſe in Latin, wherein he repreſented. That he had no greater Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction than the Diviſions he obſerv'd among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, exhorting the Biſhops very earneſtly to Peace. An<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Interpreter afterwards turn'd the Speech into Greek, for the Eaſtern Biſhops underſtood not Latin.</p>
            <p>Although it ſeems, that Buſineſs was prepared in particular Aſſemblies before hand, yet there aroſe at
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:61363:24"/>firſt a great Controverſie; and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had the patience to hear long Conteſts, wherein he exerciſed the Office of Moderator, in endeavouring to accord thoſe, whoſe Sentiments or Expreſſions appear'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, in upholding the Arguments which ſeem'd to him weak, and in giving Praiſes to ſuch, who ſeem'd to ſpeak well. <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea</hi> long held our againſt the uſe which they would<note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. &amp;c. <hi>Theod. lib.</hi> i. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> make of the Word <hi>Conſubſtantial.</hi> He offered another Confeſſion of Faith, wherein it was omitted, and wherein he call'd the Son barely, <hi>God</hi> born <hi>of God, Light of Light, Life of Life, only Son, firſt born of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, begotten of his Father before all Worlds.</hi> The Emperor approv'd this Confeſſion of Faith, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the Fathers of the Synod to follow it, in adding thereto only the Word <hi>Conſubſtantial.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards the Confeſſion was read, which had been drawn up with this Word, the Terms of which have been already recited. Anathema's were joyn'd thereto, againſt thoſe who ſhould uſe on this Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on other Terms, than thoſe of the Holy Scripture, which muſt be underſtood, with an Exception of thoſe, which the Council thought fit to confecrate. This Propoſition was particularly condemn'd, <hi>That the Son exiſted not before he was begotten. Euſebias,</hi> and others requeſted, That the Terms of the Symbol, and Anathema's might be explain'd.
<list>
                  <item>1. It was ſaid, That the Word <hi>Begotten,</hi> was uſed and not made, becauſe this laſt Word expreſſes the Production of Creatures, to which the Son has no likeneſs, being of a Subſtance far more excellent than they, begotten by the Father in an incomprehenſible manner.</item>
                  <item>2. As for the Word <hi>Conſubſtantial,</hi> it is proper to the Son, not in the ſenſe wherein it is taken, when we ſpeak
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61363:24"/>of Bodies, or mortal Animals, the Son being Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial with the Father, neither by a Diviſion of the Divine Subſtance, of which he poſſeſſes a part, nor by any change of this ſame Subſtance. The mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which is only this, That the Son has no Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance with the Creatures which he has made, but, that he is in all things like to his Father, by whom he has been begotten; or that he is not of another Hypoſtaſis, or Subſtance, but of that of the Father.</item>
                  <item>3. Thoſe were condemn'd, who ſaid, that the Son was not before he was born, ſeeing that he exiſted before his corporal Birth, and even before his divine Generation, according to <hi>Conſtantin</hi>'s Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note n="(a)">Theſe Words of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi>'s Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are not to be found but in <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, Socrates</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched them.</note> 
                     <hi>For before,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>that he was actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally begotten, he was in Power in his Father, in a manner unbegotten, the Father having been always Father, as he is ever always King and Saviour, and all things in his Power, being eternally in the ſame Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>It will perhaps ſeem, that this is pure <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> and that this is to deny the Eternity of the Son; but we muſt obſerve, that in the Style of that time, to exiſt before the World, and to be eternal, is the ſame thing; ſeeing, that to prove his Eternity, this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is cited,<note n="(b)">Vid Ep. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandri Ep.</note> 
               <hi>In the Beginning was the Word;</hi> and it ſufficed to ſhew, that he was begotten, before there was any time. So that we muſt not reject theſe Words, as ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, meerly for this Reaſon; and it is ſo ordinary to find hard Expreſſions, in thoſe who attempt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, in any ſort, this incomprehenſible Myſtery; that if one might hence judge of them, one would be apt to declare them all Hereticks, which is to ſay, to anathemize the greateſt part of the Ancients,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61363:25"/>Beſides this St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> who<note n="(a)">De. Deret. Nican. Tom. l. pag. <hi>251.</hi>
               </note> openly treats <hi>Euſebius</hi> as an <hi>Arian,</hi> makes alluſion to one part of this paſſage, and draws thence a conſequence which <hi>Euſebius</hi> without doubt would not have owned, which is, that the <hi>Arians</hi> believed that the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt did not exiſt before his corporal Birth.</p>
            <p>After theſe explications <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſubſcribed, as he himſelf teſtifies in the Letter above recited,<note n="(b)">Athanaſ. ibid.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' he had refuſed it the day before. The long and formal oppoſition which he had made againſt the word Conſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, cauſed it to be ſuſpected that there was want of ſincerity in this ſubſcription. In fine <hi>Arius</hi> and his Party were anathematized, and all their Books condemned, and particularly a Poem which <hi>Arius</hi> had entituled <hi>Thalia.</hi> Moſt of the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops ſubſcribed, after <hi>Eueſebius</hi> his example, to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith and the Anathema's after the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions above mentioned. Yet there were ſome of 'em, who refuſed at firſt to ſign,<note n="(a)">Socr. lib. l. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> the principal of which were <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia, Theognis</hi> of <hi>Nice, Maris</hi> of <hi>Calcedon, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> of <hi>Marmarica</hi> and <hi>Secondus</hi> of <hi>Ptole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maida.</hi> They were immediately Excommunicated by the Council, and were to be ſent afterwards as well as <hi>Arius,</hi> into <hi>Exile</hi> by <hi>Conſtantin.</hi> The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil wrote a circular Letter<note n="(b)">Socr. lib. l. Cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> to the Churches of <hi>Egypt,</hi> denoting to 'em in what ſort they had carried themſelves in the buſineſs of <hi>Arius,</hi> and what had been ordered touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Melece</hi> the Schiſmatical Biſhop, and the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Eaſter. Conſtantin</hi> wrote alſo to the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to aſſure it that after a full and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61363:25"/>mature examination, <hi>Arius</hi> had been condemned by the common conſent. He greatly vaunted of the moderation and learning of the Biſhops, making no mention of their quarrels, according to the Cuſtom obſerved in publick Acts, and ſuch like occaſions, where every thing is ſuppreſt which may give an ill opinion of the Decrees of theſe kinds of Aſſemblies. In another Letter directed to the Biſhops and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, he enjoyns the name of <hi>Porphyrus</hi> to be given to <hi>Arius,</hi> and his followers to be called <hi>Porphyrians.</hi> This <hi>Porphyry</hi> was a famous <hi>Platonist,</hi> who had written againſt the Chriſtian Religion, and whoſe Books <hi>Conſtantin</hi> had caus'd to be burnt. <hi>Lucas Holſtenius</hi> has written his Life, which is to be found at the end of the Book <hi>of the Abſtinence of Animals. Conſtantin</hi> deſign'd to declare hereby <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> an Enemy to the Chriſtian Religion, and not in any manner reproach him with being a Platoniſt, touching the Trinity, ſeeing <hi>Conſtantin</hi> did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve, as we have ſeen, the ſentiments of <hi>Plato.</hi> It's true the <hi>Arians</hi> have been upbraided with their too great application to the reading of this Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and other Heathen Authors: <hi>Revera de Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonis et Ariſtophanis ſinu,</hi> ſays St. Jerom,<note n="(a)">Adverſ. Lucif. T. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in episcopatum alleguntur. Quotus enim quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eſt qui non apprime in his eraditus ſit? Accedit ad hoc quod Ariana haereſis magis cum ſapientia ſeculi facit, et argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionum rivos de Ariſtotelis fontibus matuaetur.</hi> Thus the Orthodox and Hereticks equally approved the ſentiments of <hi>Plato,</hi> each of them apparently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining them, according to his Hypotheſis. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin</hi> further ordered in the fame Letter to burn all <hi>Arius</hi> his Books; <hi>to the end that not only his perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions Doctrin be deſtroyed, but that there remain no
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61363:26"/>monument of it to poſterity. He likewiſe declared that if any one concealed any of his Books, and did not bring them to be burnt, he ſhould be put to death after it had been proved upon him.</hi> There is moreover another Letter of this Emperor, wherein he enjoyns all Churches to celebrate <hi>Eaſter,</hi> according to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis,</hi> either effectually believing that the Creed of the Council might admit an <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſenſe,<note n="(a)">Soctat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> or affrighted by the Emperors ſeverity, offered to ſign the Creed, but refuſed to anathematize <hi>Arius,</hi> affirming that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions were attributed to him which he never did one; <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſo ordered, by the means of his Friends, about the Emperor,<note n="(b)">ex. Epiſt. Conſt. ad Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comed. ap. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> that what he deſired was granted him, which is to ſay, that they were contented with his ſubſcription to the Creed. <hi>Theognis</hi> and <hi>Maris</hi> did as much; and the Letter of the Council to the Churches of <hi>Egypt</hi> mentions only <hi>Theonas,</hi> and <hi>Secondus</hi> who had abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſtood out. <hi>Phyloſtorgus</hi> likewiſe acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges<note n="(a)">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. &amp; 9.</note> that all the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops ſubſcribed except two; and reproaches the reſt, with their inſincerity in that they had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd after the <hi>Arian</hi> faſhion the terms of the Council, by the advice of <hi>Conſtantia</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Siſter. He adds that <hi>Secondus</hi> ſetting out to go into his Exile, ſaid to <hi>Euſebius; you have ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,</hi> Euſebius, <hi>that you might not be baniſht, but for my part I believe what God has revealed to me, which is, that you ſhall be carried into Exile, before the year comes about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius,</hi> if we believe the Orthodox; had not the Courage to reſolve on Baniſhment, with <hi>Secondus</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61363:26"/>
               <hi>Theonas.</hi> He pretended a deſire to be better inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſought an occaſion of conferring with <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> Deacon of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
               <note n="(b)">Athan. T. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>111.</hi>
               </note> whoſe Acts are ſtill extant. If this Relation be true, one may conjecture, That <hi>Arius</hi> deſignedly defended himſelf but ill, the better to yield to his Adverſaries Reaſons, as he did, to obtain his Grace. He acknowledges at the end of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, the Equality and Conſubſtantiality of the Son with the Father; after which, he ſhews himſelf entirely reclaim'd from his Error. The Fathers of the Council receiv'd him, as a Penitent, without ſetling him in his Employ; and the Emperor only forbad him to go to <hi>Alexandria. Euzoius</hi> and <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> collegues of <hi>Arius</hi> were alſo pardoned; and St. <hi>Jerome</hi> adds<note n="(a)">In Lucifer p. <hi>145.</hi> T. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> to them eight Biſhops, of which he names but three, and one Prieſt, <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia, Theognis</hi> of <hi>Nice, Saras,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Lybia;</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea.</hi> It appears from the ſequel of the Dialogue, that the <hi>Arians</hi> denied that the Biſhops of their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were reconciled at <hi>Nice,</hi> but St. <hi>Jerom</hi> grounds himſelf on the Acts and Subſcriptions: of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, which yet he had not then at hand, excuſing himſelf from naming the four other reconciled Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops by a Rhetorical Figure, <hi>&amp; reliqui, quos enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare longumeſt.</hi> There needed not ſo much time for to ſet down four names, but without doubt, he did not remember them.</p>
            <p>The firſt who ſign'd the Council among the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, was <hi>Hoſius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cordova,</hi> afterwards, <hi>Vito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and <hi>Vincent,</hi> Roman Prieſts, ſent by <hi>Sylveſter;</hi> after them, the Biſhops of <hi>Alexandria, Antioch</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and in fine, the other Biſhops. Thoſe who favour the Pretenſions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:61363:27"/>ſay, That <hi>Hoſius</hi> ſign'd in Quality of Legat, from the Biſhop of that City, but the moſt ancient Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians have not a Word of it.</p>
            <p>The Council ending the 25th of <hi>Auguſt, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> took his farewel of them, in a very fine Harangue,<note n="(a)">Euſeb. in vit. ejus</note> wherein he exhorted the Fathers to thoughts of Peace, and to a mutual For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance; but which, was of little Effect, as will appear by the Sequel. Thus ended this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Council, the Circumſtances of which, would be better known to us, if the fear of offending great Perſons, the Zeal of ſome, the Paſſion of others, and the Reſpect which Poſterity has had for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions of ſo famous an Aſſembly, had not hindred contemporary Authors from writing the Hiſtory with exactneſs, and the Diſengagement remarkable in good Hiſtorians; and retain'd thoſe who have liv'd ſince, from ſaying what they knew (perhaps) that was diſadvantagious. St. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in a little Treatiſe already cited, and where he ſeems at firſt to be willing to enter on this Hiſtory, tranſported by the Zeal of which he was full, falls on Controverſie and Invectives; when one might expect him ready to relate Circumſtances. <hi>Sozomen</hi> ſays, <hi>That he did not dare to relate the Creed of</hi> Nice,<note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe ſome of his pious and learned Friends in this matter, adviſed him to ſuppreſs the things, which the Initiates, and the Prieſts alone ſhould underſtand, and that according to their Council, he had conceal'd what was to be kept ſilent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A while after, the Emperor<note n="(b)">Sozom. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> being to celebrate the Feaſt of his <hi>Vicennales,</hi> which is to ſay, of the twentieth Year of his Empire, invited the Biſhops to <hi>Byzantia,</hi> which he thought of re-eſtabliſhing, in giving it the new
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61363:27"/>Name of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where he magnificently treated them, and made each of 'em a-part a Preſent, after which, they return'd to their Biſhopricks. It ſeems, that it was about this time, that he wrote very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Letters to <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi>
               <note n="(c)">Socr. lib <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> in giving him order to procure him fifty Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies fairly written, of the Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>As to <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> his Friend, they were no ſooner return'd into their Biſhopricks, but they began again to Preach publickly <hi>Arianiſm,</hi>
               <note n="(d)">Ex. Epi. Conſt. ad Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. l.</note> and receiv'd into their Communion ſome Perſons of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who had been thence expelled for this Opinion. <hi>Conſtantin</hi> advertiſed of this, ſent them into Exile, three Months after the Council, and eſtabliſh'd at <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comedia</hi> one <hi>Amphion</hi> for Biſhop, and <hi>Chreſtus</hi> at <hi>Nice.</hi> Thus was <hi>Secondus</hi>'s Prediction accompliſh'd, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerity puniſhed.</p>
            <p>Two Months after, <hi>Alexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> died, which occaſion'd great Diſturbances in that City. The Orthodox<note n="(a)">Sozom. II. <hi>17.</hi> Philoſt. III. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> ſay, that <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> Deacon of this Church, whom <hi>Alexander</hi> had brought along with him to <hi>Nice,</hi> by reaſon of his Knowledge, had been denoted ſeveral times by this Biſhop, for his Succeſſor, but that he had hid himſelf a little before his Death, for fear of being Elected, and that having been found, he was choſen by a Plurality of Voices.</p>
            <p>The Heterodox affirm, on the contrary, that the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letians</hi> being re-united to the Catholicks, after the Death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> fifty-four Biſhops of <hi>Egypt</hi> took an Oath, to elect by common conſent his Succeſſor, but that ſeven among them broke their Oaths, and choſe <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius,</hi> without the Participation of the reſt. Some even aſſure, that the Voices were divided, and the Election not being made quick enough, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſhut himſelf
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61363:28"/>up with two Biſhops, into St. <hi>Denys's</hi> Church, and cauſed himſelf to be conſecrated maugre the other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, who made the Church-doors be broken open, but too late, the Ceremony being over. Hereupon they Excommunicated him; but having ſtrengthn'd his Party, he wrote in the Name of the City to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, to give him Notice of his Election, which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by this Prince, who believ'd theſe Letters came effectually from the Magiſtracy of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> There may have been Paſſion on the ſide of the Heterodox; but heating our ſelves as we do, for the Truth, as well as for Errour, and upholding ſometimes the right ſide by indirect ways, we may admit of ſome things which the Heterodox ſay, and not blindly receive, whatever the Orthodox relate.</p>
            <p>It ſeems about this time, <hi>Conſtantin</hi> made his Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution<note n="a">Euſeb. in ejus vit. lib. <hi>III.</hi> c. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> againſt the meetings of all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, wherein he forbids them to aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble either in publick or private, gives their Chappels to Catholicks, and confiſcates the Houſes wherein they are found to meet, performing their Devotions. <hi>Euſebius</hi> adds, that the Emperors Edict moreover contain'd, that all Heretical Books ſhould be ſeiz'd on; and that <hi>Conſtantin</hi>'s threatnings obliged a great number of Hereticks and Schiſmaticks to range themſelves on the ſide of the Orthodox Church. But ſome doing of it ſincerely, and others by force, the Biſhops applied themſelves carefully to diſtinguiſh them, and receiv'd only into the Church thoſe who were real Converts. The <hi>Arians</hi> had been ruin'd by particular Edicts, ſo that all Hereſies ſeem'd to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in the Roman Empire.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> who had at firſt ſlighted the ſubject of the Diſpute, between <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting only of different Expreſſions, and who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards had conſidered it, as a Point of the greateſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61363:28"/>return'd again to a good Opinion of <hi>Arius;</hi> whether he acted according to his preſent Intereſts, or that he ſuffered himſelf to be led by thoſe who were moſt about him, or that in fine, he really chang'd his Opinion.<note n="a">Socrat. lib. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi> ex Ruffin.</note> 
               <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> Siſter of <hi>Conſtantin</hi> and Widow of <hi>Licinus,</hi> had among her Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks, a Prieſt, a friend to <hi>Arius,</hi> who held the ſame Opinions as he did, and who perſwaded this Princeſs, that <hi>Arius</hi> held not thoſe Opinions he he was charged with, in the manner as they were uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally expreſs'd, that <hi>Alexander</hi> had accuſed him through Envy, becauſe he was eſteem'd by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and that the Council had done him wrong. <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> who much confided in this Prieſt, eaſily believ'd him, but dared not ſpeak her Mind to the Emperour; and being fall'n dangerouſly ſick, all that ſhe could do before ſhe died, was to recommend this Prieſt to her Brother, as a man highly vertuous, and much devoted to the ſervice of her Family. A while after ſhe died, and this Prieſt having gotten the favour of <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> held to him the ſame Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, telling him, That if he pleas'd to admit <hi>Arius</hi> to come before him, and to explain his Opinion, he would find that at bottom, his Doctrin was the ſame as that of the Council which condemn'd him. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin</hi> ſurpriz'd at the oddneſs of this Diſcourſe, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, That if <hi>Arius</hi> would ſign the <hi>Nicexe Creed,</hi> he would let him come into his Preſence, and would ſend him honourably to <hi>Alexandria.</hi> This Prieſt having aſſured him of it, <hi>Conſtantin</hi> ſent Word to <hi>Arius</hi> to come to Court, and <hi>Arius</hi> not daring at firſt to do it, the Emperor wrote a Note to him, in which he ordered him to come immediately at his Charge: <hi>Arius</hi> obeyed this reiterated Order, and being come to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with <hi>Enzoius,</hi> they preſented to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61363:29"/>Emperor a Confeſſion of their Faith, wherein they barely ſaid, <hi>They believ'd that the Son was begotten of the Father before all Ages, and that the Reaſon, who is God, had made all things, as well in Heav'n as in Earth. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin</hi> was fully ſatisfi'd with this Declaration, ſo that either he had chang'd his Mind, or giv'n ſmall Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or little comprehended the ſenſe of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed. However it was, it appears by the Sequel, That the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops came by Degrees into favor, and that the Emperor treated <hi>Arius</hi> with great kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and permitted him to return to <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's not punctually known when <hi>Arius</hi> was re-call'd, but it's certain, he had been already, when <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> were, which hapned three years after the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> in the year 328, according to the relation of <hi>Philostorgus,</hi>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note> theſe two Biſhops wrote from the place of their Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment a Letter, wherein they complain,<note n="(b)">Socr. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That they had been condemn'd without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard, altho their conduct had been approved of in the Council, where having well examin'd the word</hi> Conſubſtantial, <hi>they had in fine approved of it. They added, they had only refuſed to Anathematize</hi> Arius, <hi>becauſe they knew he was not ſuch a one as he was deſcribed; and ſeeing this was acknowledg'd by his being recalled, it could not be juſt that they who ſuffered only on his account, ſhould remain in Exile after his Revocation. This Letter was directed to the principal Biſhops, whom</hi> Euſebius <hi>and</hi> Theognis <hi>entreated to interceed for them with the Emperor.</hi> In ſpeaking of the Repeal of <hi>Arius,</hi> they directly attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to theſe Biſhops: <hi>Your Piety,</hi> ſay they, <hi>has thought fit to treat him gently, and to recal him.</hi> A Learned man<note n="(c)">Valeſius ad locum.</note> obſerves in this place, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> attribute to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops what the Emperor had done, ſeeing
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61363:29"/>it was he that had recalled <hi>Arius;</hi> and that the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Hiſtorians attribute likewiſe ſometimes to the Emperor the actions of the Biſhops, as when <hi>Socrates</hi> ſays that the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> forbad <hi>Arius</hi> his return to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> whereas it was the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. But in truth the Emperor did then few things of his own pure motion, being only the Church men's Tool, which falls out but too often, even among the greateſt Princes.</p>
            <p>The Letter of <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> produced the affect which they hoped from it. They were recalled with <hi>Theonas</hi> and <hi>Secondus</hi> who would ſign nothing. The two firſt being returned to their Biſhopricks, drove out thence thoſe who had gotten into their Sees, when they were ſent to their places of baniſhment. They are charged with having immediately after ſought out ways to make <hi>Athanaſius</hi> undergoe the ſame puniſhment, which they came from ſuffering, by getting it told the Emperor, that he had been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected in a manner little canonical, and with endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to induce the ſame <hi>Athanaſius</hi> both by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and threatnings, to permit <hi>Arius</hi> to return to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria.</hi> However they could not then accompliſh their purpoſe; and we ſhall ſee in the ſequel the bick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erings which they had with this Biſhop.</p>
            <p>Since the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had been diſtmiſt, and that they had been baniſht. This uſage, and the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of <hi>Nice</hi> had but only outwardly allai'd the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, which laſts ſtill when they were recalled. <hi>Euſebius</hi> aſſures us that the Biſhops of <hi>Egypt</hi> had been ever ſince over Head and Ears in quarrels; and <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> ſays<note n="(a)">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 23.</note> that he found from the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Biſhops of thoſe times, that ſome were ſcandaliz'd at the word <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial; examining,</hi> ſays he, <hi>this term with too great
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61363:30"/>application, they fell foul on one another, and their quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels did not ill reſemble a combat in the dark. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears they ſufficiently beſpattered one another with calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, without knowing wherefore. Thoſe who rejected the word</hi> Conſubſtantial, <hi>thought the others hereby in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced the opinions of</hi> Sabellius <hi>and</hi> Montanus, <hi>and treated them as impious, as denying the exiſtence</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>of the Son of God. On the contrary thoſe who ſtuck to the word</hi> Conſubſtantial, <hi>imagining the others would intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a plurality of Gods, had as great averſion, as if they would have reeſtabliſht Paganiſm.</hi> Euſtathius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Antioch <hi>accuſed</hi> Euſebius <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Ceſarea <hi>for the Nicene Creed.</hi> Euſebius <hi>denied it, and charged on the other ſide</hi> Euſtathius <hi>of</hi> Sabellianiſm; <hi>thus the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops wrote one againſt another. They all accorded in ſaying the Son has a particular Exiſtence, and that there is only one God in three Hypoſtaſes; yet they could not agree, nor remain quiet.</hi> This is the effect of equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal terms, which were introduced into Chriſtianity without well defining them, and the bad cuſtom of moſt of the Ancients, who never ſpeak calmly of theſe matters; who have thought of nothing leſs than the expreſſing themſelves clearly, and who ſeem to prove they ſpake ſincerely, when they teſtified to believe, that the miſtery about which they diſputed was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible; by expreſſing themſelves thereon in an unintelligible manner. <hi>Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi>
               <note n="(a)">Socr. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> accuſing of Arianiſm <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea, Paulinus</hi> of <hi>Tyre,</hi> and <hi>Patrophilus</hi> of <hi>Scythopolis;</hi> and theſe Biſhops accuſing him in their turns of <hi>Sabellianiſm;</hi> to know who had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon on their ſide, a Synod was aſſembled at <hi>Antioch</hi> in 329. the concluſions of which were diſadvantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to <hi>Euſtathius.</hi> It conſiſted of Biſhops, who had ſign'd the Nicene Creed only by force, among whom
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61363:30"/>were the two <hi>Euſebius</hi>'s, <hi>Theognis</hi> of <hi>Nice, Theodotus</hi> of <hi>Laodicea</hi> in <hi>Syria, Narciſſus</hi> of <hi>Neroniada, Aetius</hi> of <hi>Lydiae, Alphaeus</hi> of <hi>Apamea,</hi> and <hi>Theodorus</hi> of <hi>Sidon.</hi> Aſſoon as ever they arriv'd at <hi>Antioch,</hi> a Woman of ill fame preſented her ſelf to 'em with a little Child, which ſhe ſaid to have had by <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them to do her right againſt him, as refuſing to receive his Child. <hi>Euſtathius</hi> made great proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his innocency, but this Woman having been believed upon her Oath, he was depoſed;<note n="(a)">Theod. &amp; Sozom.</note> ſome Authors affirmed that the <hi>Arian</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had ſuborn'd her, to have an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the depoſing of <hi>Euſtathius;</hi> and that the true cauſe of his depoſal was his adherence to the Nicene Creed. Others ſay it was the pretended <hi>Sabellianiſm</hi> of which he was accuſed, and ſome have contented themſelves with ſaying there were other accuſations, for which he had been depoſed, whereupon <hi>Socrates</hi>
               <note n="(b)">loco. cit.</note> makes this remarkable reflection: <hi>The Biſhops are wont to deal thus with all thoſe whom they depoſe; accuſing and declaring them impious, without ſhewing wherein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Biſhop was afterwards to be ſubſtituted in <hi>Euſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> his place, and the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops caſt their eyes on <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea.</hi> But there aroſe a violent ſedition hereupon; ſome willing to retain <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers accepting <hi>Euſebius.</hi> They had come to Fiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuffs, had not the Emperor taken care, by ſending one of his Officers who appeaſed the People, and made them underſtand how <hi>Euſtathius</hi> deſerv'd to be ſent into Exile, and in effect he was ſent into <hi>Thrace.</hi> However <hi>Euſebius</hi> did a thing, which made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive very honourable Letters from the Emperor, which he has inſerted in the life of this Prince, which is, that according to the Canons, he refuſed to paſs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61363:31"/>from one Church to another. <hi>Conſtantin</hi> heapt up Praiſes on him by reaſon of this refuſal, and wrote to the Council, and the Church of <hi>Antioch</hi> to let him remain where he was. So that inſtead of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> there was elected <hi>Euphronius</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> whom the Emperor had named with <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſa,</hi> to the end the Council might chooſe which they pleaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="(a)">Soc. <hi>1.27. &amp;</hi> Seq. Soz. Theod.</note>Having depoſed <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> the <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Biſhops labored to procure the return of <hi>Arius</hi> to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where <hi>Athanaſius</hi> would not permit him to enter, as has been already ſaid. They engaged the Emperor to write to this Biſhop, but <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſtill defended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in that he could not receive into the Church thoſe who had forſook the Faith and been excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; ſo that <hi>Conſtantin</hi> wrote to him an angry Letter, that he ſhould receive into the Church thoſe he or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him, under pain of baniſhment. The obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of this Biſhop, who would part with none of the advantages which the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> had granted to his Predeceſſor againſt the <hi>Meletians,</hi> had alſo drawn on him the enmity of theſe Schiſmaticks. The Council had ordained that <hi>Melece</hi> ſhould only retain the name of Biſhop, without exerciſing any function of his Office, and without ordaining any Succeſſor; and that thoſe whom he had ordained ſhould have no part in Elections. However <hi>Melece</hi> at his death had ordained one <hi>John</hi> for his Succeſſor, and the Meletian Prieſts would have the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges as others. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> could not conſent to any thing of this, and equally ill treated the <hi>Meletians</hi> and <hi>Arians.</hi> This conduct reunited the two parties, who had been till that time oppoſite. The <hi>Meletians</hi> were of the Nicene opinion; but by converſing with
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61363:31"/>the <hi>Arians,</hi> they ſoon entred into their Sentiments, and joyn'd together, to induce <hi>Conſtantin</hi> to accept of ſeveral Accuſations againſt <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> as hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impoſed a kind of Tribute on <hi>Egypt,</hi> in ordering it to furniſh the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain number of Linnen Garments; in having ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied a certain ſeditious Perſon with Mony; nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Philumenus;</hi> in having cauſed a Chalice to be broken, overthrown the Table of a Church, and burnt the Holy Books; for having miſ-uſed ſeveral Prieſts, and committed divers Violences; in hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cut off the Arm of a <hi>Meletian</hi> Biſhop, named <hi>Arſenius,</hi> and keeping it to uſe in Magical Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Conſtantin</hi> acknowledg'd the Innocency of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in regard of the two firſt Accuſations; and for the reſt, he refer'd it to an Aſſembly of divers Biſhops, which was at <hi>Ceſarea</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> where <hi>Athanaſius</hi> not appearing, he was cited to a Synod at <hi>Tyre,</hi> in the year 334, and which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of Biſhops of <hi>Egypt, Lybia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was in Suſpence, whether he ſhould preſent himſelf to this Synod, which conſiſted of his principal Enemies? Yet <hi>Conſtantin</hi> having threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with Baniſhment if he refuſed, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appeared, and juſtified himſelf of the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation touching the Arm of <hi>Arſinius,</hi> by bringing in this Perſon into the midſt of them, and deriding his Accuſers. It's ſaid moreover, That a Woman being introduced into the Aſſembly, accuſed him for having diſhonoured her, after ſhe had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd him in her Houſe, although he knew ſhe had made a Vow of Virginity. But it appeared, that ſhe did not ſo much as know <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe took one <hi>Timotheus,</hi> a Prieſt for him, who pretended to be the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:61363:32"/>
            <p>The buſineſs of the broken Chalice, and the miſ-uſing the Prieſts, was a little more difficult. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> began by an Appeal from <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and the reſt of the Biſhops of his Party. He afterwards ſaid, That he, whoſe Chalice was pretended to have been broken, and whoſe Name was <hi>Iſchyras,</hi> was not a Prieſt. However, without any regard to theſe Reaſons, there were ſent ſome <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, to take Informations againſt him at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> with <hi>Iſchyras</hi> his Accuſer; but he proteſted highly againſt this Proceeding, and went to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where the Emperour was. In the mean time, the Informations from <hi>Egypt</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> being loaded with them, he was depoſed in his Abſence, and forbid to go to <hi>Alexandria. Arſenius</hi> having been admitted into Communion by the Council, and made Biſhop of <hi>Hypſyle,</hi> a Town of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſubſcrib'd to the Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> although he had juſtifi'd him, in reference to one of the Accuſations brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. The Sentence of the Council bore, that he had ſlighted the Emperors Orders, and made the Aſſembly wait for him in an indecent manner; That he came to <hi>Tyre</hi> with a great multitude of People, and endeavour'd to make a Diſturbance there; That he had for ſometime re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to purge himſelf of the Crimes ſaid to his Charge, and uttered Injuries to divers Biſhops; That he would not ſubmit to their judgment; That he was convicted of breaking a Chalice, by the Informations made againſt him at <hi>Alexandria.</hi> Thus was <hi>Athanaſius</hi> condemned by his Enemies, who were his Judges, as <hi>Arius</hi> had been anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiz'd by <hi>Alexander</hi> his Predeceſſor, and ſeveral other Biſhops, who had declared themſelves againſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61363:32"/>him, before the Convocation of the Council. The ſame uſage has been obſerv'd in all the Aſſemblies of Biſhops which have met ſince; the Clergy hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Advantage above the Laity, that they can be both Judges and Parties.</p>
            <p>After the Depoſal of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the Emperor wrote to the Fathers of the Council, to repair as ſoon as poſſible to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to celebrare the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of the Church of the Apoſtles, which was now finiſhed. Where being arriv'd, they were magnificently receiv'd, and made ſeveral Orations, for the greater Solemnity of the Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val, which hapned to be very luckily, in the ſame year in which the <hi>Tricennales</hi> of the Emperor<note n="(a)">In the Year, 335.</note> were to be celebrated, which is to ſay, the 30th year of his Reign. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi>
               <note n="(b)">In vit. Conſt. lib. <hi>iv. 46,</hi> &amp; <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> particularly made ſeveral Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rang's before the Emperor, who took a great deal of pleaſure in hearing them, inſomuch that he would hear ſtanding a long Oration, which this Biſhop made on the holy Sepulchre. <hi>Euſebius</hi> well remembers this Honour the Emperor did him, and the Praiſes he gave to his Oration touching <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inſerts in the Life of <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> all the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters he had receiv'd from the Emperor; perhaps, not out of Acknowledgment, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to do himſelf Honour,<note n="(a)">Baronius ad bac tempora.</note> as has been reproach'd him.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops aſſembled at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note n="(b)">Socr. lib. <hi>l.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> having ended the Dedication of the Church, which <hi>Conſtantin</hi> had newly built, and there receiv'd into Communion <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Euzoius,</hi> on the Emperors Recommendations.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61363:33"/>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> ſay, that <hi>Arius</hi> had been <hi>kindly</hi> receiv'd by the Biſhops, but in no ſort, that he was received into Communion, which was, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, for ſome years refuſed him, to try his Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Afterwards they wrote to the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> that ſhe might receive them, and be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, ſhe would enjoy hence-forward a full Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility, Envy having been driv'n out thence, by the Depoſal of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi>
               <note n="(a)">
                  <hi>Sozom. lib.</hi> II. 28.</note> In the mean time this Biſhop had gotten to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> to complain to the Emperor of what he had ſuffered; but he could obtain no Audience of him; all that he could be heard to ſay, was, That he entreated the Emperor to cire to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> the Biſhops which were at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> to have another Examination of his Affair. <hi>Conſtantin</hi> wrote to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and complains in his Letter, that in a time wherein the <hi>Barbarians</hi> began to acknowledge the true God; <q>The Chriſtians, who would be thought to have the My ſteries of God in their keeping, (for he durſt not ſay that they kept them,) labour'd only to entertain Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and hatred among them, not to ſay, for the Deſtruction of Mankind.</q> And therefore he deſired that the Biſhops aſſembled at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> would meet at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to examine once for all, the Affair of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and put ſome end to it. This Letter being come to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſome of the Biſhops return'd to their Dioceſes, and others to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Theſe laſt perſwaded, according to ſome Authors,<note n="(a)">Id.</note> the Emperor, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> had effectually broken a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice; or according to others,<note n="(b)">Socr. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> that he had threatned to ſtop the Convoy of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61363:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>Proviſions which went every year from <hi>Alexandria</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> of which three Biſhops were Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. The Emperor provoked by theſe Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ordered him to retire to <hi>Treves,</hi> a Town of the <hi>Belgick Gaule,</hi> where he remain'd about two years.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops who were met at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>
               <note n="(c)">id. cap. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> depoſed after this <hi>Marcellus</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyra,</hi> as being fall'n into the opinion of <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſatia.</hi> One <hi>Aſterius</hi> who had taught Rhetorick in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> having embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Chriſtian Religion, had wrote ſome Books, wherein he ſpake of the Divinity of the Son, in the ſame terms as <hi>Arius. Marcellus</hi> undertook to refute them, but far from eſtabliſhng the Pre-exiſtence of the Son, he denied the Divinity of Jeſus Chriſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſted before his Birth; or at leaſt expreſt himſelf in ſuch a manner, that one might believe he regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Reaſon or the Word, not as a being that has his particular Exiſtence, but as I know not what kind of accident, ſuch as is the word, or the found which is made in ſpeaking. He alſo very ill treated<note n="(a)">Euſeb. cont. Marcel. lib. l. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> in the ſame Book ſeveral <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, as the two <hi>Euſebius</hi>'s, <hi>Paulinus</hi> and <hi>Narciſſus.</hi> He charged like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Origen</hi> for expounding the Holy Scripture, according to the notions of heathen Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, and eſpecially according to thoſe of <hi>Plato;</hi> from whom <hi>Marcellus</hi> affirmed, he had taken his Doctrin of Principles, which is to ſay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Holy Trinity, of which he had treated after the Platon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick faſhion. The <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops offended with this Book, had begun to examin it, when they were as yet at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> but having been obliged to paſs
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61363:34"/>over to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> they had only enjoyned <hi>Marcellus to alter his Opinion,</hi> according to the Stile of that time. He promiſt he would burn his Book, but having not done it, and even refuſing to do it, his affair was reaſſumed at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and he was depoſed. <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea</hi> wrote two Books expreſly againſt him, wherein he criticizes his work, and three others which he entituled, of <hi>Eccleſiaſtick Theology,</hi> wherein he eſtabliſht the opinions which he thought Orthodox touching the Divinity, and refuted thoſe of <hi>Marcellus</hi> and divers other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. <hi>Marcellus</hi> was afterwards<note n="(a)">Socr. lib. II. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; Soz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>om. lib. II. cap. <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> reeſtabliſht in the Synod of <hi>Sardica;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he affirmed his expreſſions had been miſunderſtood; and being an Enemy to the <hi>Arians,</hi> he inſinuated Himſelf into the Friendſhip of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> who perhaps was ſurpriz'd by the Equivocal Expreſſions uſed by <hi>Marcellus.</hi> It's certain, that if we may judge of him by the Fragments which <hi>Euſebius</hi> cites, he ſcarcely knew what he would ſay himſelf, or elſe he conceal'd his Opinions under obſcure terms, leſt he ſhould fall into trouble.</p>
            <p>After that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> had been ſent into Exile,<note n="(a)">id. lib. I. c. <hi>27.</hi> &amp; ſeq.</note> 
               <hi>Arius</hi> had returned to <hi>Alexandria;</hi> but his preſence being likely to cauſe a diſorder, by reaſon of the great number of thoſe who followed the ſentiments of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the Emperor recalled this Prieſt to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and to aſſure himſelf entirely of his belief, of which the Orthodox ſtill doubted, he offered him the Nicene Creed to ſign, which he did without ballancing, and moreover ſwore he was of that opinion. A report ran that he had
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61363:34"/>hid under his Arm a Writing, which contain'd his Opinion, and that he barely ſwore he believ'd what he had wrote; but there is no great certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be expected in what his Enemies ſay of him. Perhaps he thought, like <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> that one might give to the words of the Creed a ſenſe which amounted to his ſentiment, although he wiſht they had made uſe of other terms. What the Fathers of <hi>Nice</hi> ſaid more than he conſiſting in in ſomething abſolutely incomprehenſible; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps moreover he counted that for nothing. However <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to receive him into Communion, although the Emperor had ordered him to do it, and a great number of Biſhops and of the People urged him to it. Beſides this the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops were preparing to hold a Council, to examin afreſh the queſtion agitated at <hi>Nice,</hi> and had markt a day in which they were to meet to diſcourſe about it, and to conduct <hi>Arius</hi> into the Church maugre <hi>Alexander.</hi> In this extremity knowing not how to maintain his refuſal, the Hiſtory tells us that he ſhut himſelf up in a Church call'd <hi>Peace,</hi> and ſet himſelf very devoutly to pray to God, not that he would convert <hi>Arius,</hi> or that he would diſcover to himſelf the Truth, but, <hi>that if the opinion of</hi> Arius <hi>was true, he himſelf might not ſee the day ſet apart to diſcourſe of it; or that if his own belief were true,</hi> Arius <hi>who was the cauſe of ſo great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, might be puniſht for his Infidelity.</hi> A Prayer ſo little charitable, and whence might be ſeen that this Biſhop was more concern'd for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation than the Truth, fail'd not of being heard, ſeeing that the next morning which was
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61363:35"/>Sunday, or the ſame day at night, as <hi>Arius</hi> went to the Church accompani'd by thoſe of his Party, or in ſome other place, for the Hiſtorians vary, in paſſing by the Market of <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> he had ſo great occaſion to go to eaſe himſelf, that he was forced to betake himſelf to the common Privies, where inſtead of finding eaſe, he evacuated his Bowels, and thus died ſuddenly. Since that time Paſſengers were commonly ſhew'd theſe places of eaſement, and no body dared ſit down on the ſame place where <hi>Arius</hi> ſat. 'Tis ſaid that a Rich <hi>Arian,</hi> to aboliſh the memory of it, bought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards this Place of the Publick, and there built an Houſe.</p>
            <p>It's thus that <hi>Rufinus, Socrates,</hi> and <hi>Sozomen</hi> relate the laſt Events of the life of <hi>Arius.</hi> But St. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſays that<note n="(a)">in Epſt. ad Serapionem.</note> having been recalled by the ſolicitations of thoſe of his Party, he offered his Confeſſion of Faith to the Emperor, and ſwore that he did not believe any thing elſe; after which thoſe that protected him would introduce him into the Church, at his going out of the Emperors Palace, but that he died, without having been received into Communion.<note n="(b)">De. Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis.</note> A Learned Man is of Opinion in this matter, <hi>That the</hi> Arius <hi>who was received into Communion at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>was a Prieſt of the Party of the famous</hi> Arius, <hi>and not he himſelf, who had already died out of the Communion of the Church;</hi> for without this it muſt be ſaid that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> has been miſtaken. But were it granted him that this Biſhop was miſtaken, in ſpeaking of a Man whom he every moment orewhelmed with injuries, it cannot be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61363:35"/>found ſtrange, eſpecially not having been at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> then, when what he relates muſt have hapned. One may farther ſay, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> has related, by way of abridgment, and little exactly, what he had heard ſay of <hi>Arius,</hi> and that he regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him as an excommunicated Perſon, having been only received by a Council whoſe Authority <hi>Athanaſius</hi> would not acknowledge, it conſiſting principally of Perſons whoſe opinions had been ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematized at <hi>Nice.</hi> It is far more natural thus to interpret this paſſage of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject wholly as falſe an Hiſtory ſo circumſtanc'd as that of the latter years of the life of <hi>Arius,</hi> in reſpect of certain facts which the Hiſtorians, which we have already cited, had no intereſt to alter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius</hi> being dead, apparently of a ſudden death, peradventure by Poyſon, which may have given occaſion to the Tragical manner, in which the Hiſtorians mention it, the Diſputes ſtarted on his occaſion dyed not with him:<note n="(a)">Soz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. lib. II. c. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> Thoſe who were of <hi>Athanaſius's</hi> Party at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> beſought of God his return in the Publick Prayers, and ceaſed not to impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the Emperor, to make him be recalled. <hi>Conſtantin</hi> was oblig'd to write to the People of that Town a Letter, wherein he upbraided them for their Lightneſs and Folly, and enjoyns the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks to remain quiet, and wherein he declares he would not recall <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> whom he treats as a ſeditious Perſon, and one who had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by a Council. He anſwers likewiſe to <hi>Anthony</hi> the Hermit; <hi>That he could not ſlight the Judgment of the Council of</hi> Tyre, <hi>becauſe that ſuppoſing ſome among the Biſhops were paſſionate, yet it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:61363:36"/>that ſo great a number of Wiſe and Learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhould all of 'em act by paſſion; and that</hi> Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>was an Inſolent Proud and Troubleſom Fellow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantin</hi> wrote theſe Letters but a little time before his death, which hapned in the year 337, the circumſtances of which may be ſeen in his life writ by <hi>Euſebius.</hi> Yet we muſt remember, that this is rather a Panegyrick than an unintereſt Hiſtory; whence it is that he ſays nothing of the death of his two Wives, and the eldeſt Son of this Emperor, whom he had put to death thro' jealouſy or revenge. <hi>Euſebius</hi> was always of the <hi>Arians</hi> ſide. Yet <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> has undertaken to juſtifie him,<note n="(b)">Socr. lib. II. c. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> and ſo do's Dr. <hi>Cave</hi> ſeem to do, thinking himſelf thereto obliged thro' Chriſtian Charity; whereas the love of truth ſhould oblige all Hiſtorians never to vary from i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But it is this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended charity, which extends it ſelf only to Fathers which are reſpected as Orthodox, which has been the cauſe that we have in a manner only Panegyricks of the Ancients, wherein their defects are ever ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt; when they cannot be covered with the mask of ſome Vertues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> as it appears by the conduct he held at the Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> was a dextrous Perſon, who did not ſcruple to ſubſcribe to terms which were not pleaſing to him, provided he could expound them in a ſenſe according to his mind, tho' little conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to that of thoſe who ſet them up. For in fine, a Man muſt ſhut his Eyes, touching what he ſays in his Letter to the Church of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> not to ſee, that he underſtood otherwiſe the terms of the Symbol, than <hi>Athanaſius</hi> did. He was a great admirer of <hi>Origen,</hi> ſeveral of whoſe opinions may be ſeen in his life; he lived not long after <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> for he dyed in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61363:36"/>the year 340. St. <hi>Jerome</hi> in ſeveral places calls him <hi>Signifer et Princeps Arianorum;</hi> Speaking of the great <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſarea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his baniſhment wrote a Creed at <hi>Rome,</hi> which he preſented to a Council ſitting there, yet that Creed was not publiſh'd till above three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after in the <hi>Toletan</hi> Council, as <hi>Baronius</hi> himſelf owns, neither can any one tell us what that was; for that which paſſes commonly amongſt us under the name of the <hi>Athanaſian Creed,</hi> and is read in our Churches, was drawn up by God knows who, as <hi>Voſſius de Tribus Symbolis, Camerarius,</hi> and <hi>Ell. du Pin in his B. des Aut. Eccleſ.</hi> do ingenuouſly confeſs. For how durſt <hi>Athanaſius</hi> make a new Creed after the Nicene? Beſides, no Writer of that time mentions it, no not <hi>Athanaſius</hi> himſelf. It ſeems to have been broach't above 600 years after that age, in which time a profound ignorance had overſpread Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; however the Eaſtern Churches would never own it, no not at this day. See more in the above mentioned learned Authors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantin</hi> being dead, <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nicome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> a refin'd Courtier, ſoon made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and all the Grandees of the Palace, in whom he rooted his beloved <hi>Arianiſm;</hi> being aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Conſtantia's</hi> Prieſt, the Empreſs was ſoon gain'd over, and the Roman Empire became for the moſt part <hi>Arian, Athanaſius</hi> being condemn'd not only by many Eaſtern, but alſo by ſeveral great Weſtern Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. Afterwards they fell ſo to <hi>Logger-heads,</hi> that the Weſtern Church excommunicated the Eaſtern, and the Eaſtern return'd the ſame Complement upon the Weſtern, and there we'll leave them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
